<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An essay to revive the necessity of the ancient charity and piety wherein God's right in our estates and our obligations to maintain his service, religion, and charity is demonstrated and defended against the pretences of covetousness and appropriation : in two discourses written to a person of honour and vertue / by George Burghope.</title>
            <author>G. B. (George Burghope)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 218 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 113 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5732</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26568</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09501900</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09501900</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43329</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30298)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43329)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1326:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An essay to revive the necessity of the ancient charity and piety wherein God's right in our estates and our obligations to maintain his service, religion, and charity is demonstrated and defended against the pretences of covetousness and appropriation : in two discourses written to a person of honour and vertue / by George Burghope.</title>
                  <author>G. B. (George Burghope)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 189 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Piety.</term>
               <term>Charity.</term>
               <term>Theological virtues.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43329:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43329:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ESSAY TO Revive the Neceſſity OF THE <hi>Ancient Charity and Piety.</hi> WHEREIN God's Right in our Eſtates, and our Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to maintain his Service, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and Charity, is demonſtrated and defended, againſt the Pretences of Covetouſneſs and Appropriation.</p>
            <p>In Two Diſcourſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written to a Perſon of Honour and Vertue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>George Burghope,</hi> Rector of <hi>Little Gaddeſden,</hi> Com. <hi>Hertford,</hi> and Chaplain to the Right Honourable <hi>JOHN</hi> Earl of <hi>Bridgwater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Luke 16. 9. <hi>And I ſay unto you, Make you friends,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop's-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul'</hi>s Church-Yard, 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:43329:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Humf. Hody, <hi>R. in Ch. P. ac D. D.</hi> Johanni <hi>Div. Prov. Archiep. Cant. à Sac. Dom.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Sept. 26. 1694.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:43329:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God <hi>THOMAS</hi> Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> Primate of all <hi>England,</hi> and Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, and one of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's moſt Honourable Privy Council, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Grace,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TO pardon the Preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of one of the Clergy of Your late Dioceſs, and of Your preſent Province, in this Addreſs; one who had never the honour to ſee your Perſon, but in your
<pb facs="tcp:43329:3"/> Epiſcopal Viſitation, where he obſerv'd, with a mixture of Contentment and Admiration, the Humility, Condeſcention, and Paternal Tenderneſs to your Clergy; when you might have come with a Rod, you choſe to viſit us in Love, and the Spirit of Meekneſs; by which you ſubdu'd every Heart to Obedience, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all our Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But, <hi>my Lord,</hi> you have a more eſpecial Title to theſe <hi>Papers</hi> from your <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> which are their Argument: Of both which (even then when you were but a private <hi>Presbyter</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi>) you gave ſo large a Specimen in your own Pariſh,
<pb facs="tcp:43329:3"/> and in dangerous Times, that it remains as a laſting Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a ſufficient Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of what you durſt then, and what you will do ſtill for the Support of that <hi>Church</hi> of which you are deſervedly now the <hi>Chief Member.</hi> And we have all the reaſon in the World to congratulate your Advancement to the <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>epiſcopal Throne,</hi> (as the <hi>Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents</hi> uſe to call it) not ſo much for your Happineſs as our own. And ſo much the more, when we remember that we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Care</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Leader,</hi> who is an Example to us all, in <hi>Word,</hi> in <hi>Converſation,</hi> in <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> in <hi>Faith,</hi> and in <hi>Purity.</hi> One, who (having regularly
<pb facs="tcp:43329:4"/> paſt through all the Degrees of the <hi>Clergy</hi> to the higheſt <hi>Place</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi>) knows the Nature and Circumſtances of all its Members, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently will take all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to encourage the Inferior as well as Superior <hi>Parts</hi> of that Auguſt <hi>Body:</hi> The poor <hi>Curates</hi> (that do the whole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Duties ſometimes of great Pariſhes for ſmall Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends) and the pooreſt <hi>Vicars,</hi> (diſ-ſpirited and diſpoſſeſs'd of the ancient <hi>Demeſns</hi> of their <hi>Churches,</hi> and forc'd with their Families to live upon the Tythes of <hi>Mint, Aniſe,</hi> and <hi>Cummin,</hi> &amp;c,) as well as the Reverend <hi>Dignitaries,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of larger Revenues.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43329:4"/>
            <p>And, in a word, when we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that You are not only a prudent and careful <hi>Governor,</hi> but a skilful <hi>Pilot,</hi> who will omit no Diligence or Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities to Steer the late toſſed Ship of our <hi>Church</hi> amongſt ſo many Rocks and Waves, private and publick Enemies, into the Haven of <hi>Proſperity</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi> To which the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> in his preſent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, can only contribute theſe his <hi>Papers</hi> and his <hi>Prayers;</hi> who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               <signed>Your Graces Moſt dutiful Son, and Humble Servant, Geo. Burghope.</signed>
               <dateline>From <hi>Little Gaddeſden</hi> in the County of <hi>Hertf.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 12. 1695.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="premonition_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:43329:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43329:5"/>
            <head>A PREMONITION TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>WHen the Author had been perſuaded to make theſe Diſcourſes publick, he thought it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary alſo to ſay ſomething in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of ſuch Publication, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that even in theſe bad Times they are not unſuitable, nor poſſibly unfruitful.</p>
            <p>For the firſt Part, it will make ſhift for it ſelf, and carry its own A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology,
<pb facs="tcp:43329:6"/> even with the moſt Selfiſh and Covetous. For thoſe that will not be perſuaded by it themſelves, will yet be willing that others ſhould, if it be but to ſpare their own Pockets; for the more is done in that part of Charity which conſiſts in relieving of the Poor, the leſs is left to be done. And ſeeing the Poor we muſt have always with us, and they muſt be always maintain'd by us, the Miſer is eas'd and gratified by another's Bounty.</p>
            <p>But then for the latter Part, which is a Perſuaſive to Works of Piety, the very Attempt ſeems to be ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and the Author expects he ſhall be loudly laugh'd at as a ſilly Fellow, that, in ſuch an Age as this is, ſhou'd think to perſuade Men to part with their beloved <hi>Mammon</hi> to ſuch Uſes. And tho' he has conſidered the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:43329:6"/> of this Nature towards the latter end of the Diſcourſe it ſelf, yet it well be proper here to prevent thoſe that he hath not there ſpoken to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently, or not at all. And thoſe are theſe Three: <hi>Firſt,</hi> The univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal decay of Religion it ſelf. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> That of the particular Church yet by Law eſtabliſhed. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The general Averſion there is almoſt in all Men to Works of this Nature: Of which in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, We are told that Religion (which he wou'd in this Diſcourſe embelliſh and adorn by ſuch Acceſſions) is in it ſelf ſick and decaying, and its very Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons much weakned; and therefore it wou'd be more ſerviceable to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſecure them, than adorn its
<pb facs="tcp:43329:7"/> 
               <hi>Frontiſpiece.</hi> And, indeed, if we conſider the many Apoſtates from its Doctrines and Government, and the more from the Practice of thoſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties it enjoyns, we ſhall have but a melancholy Proſpect of the preſent State of Religion. Cuſtom and the Charity of the Church hath indeed brought us into its Boſom in our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, and we ſtill retain the Name of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> as moſt Creditable and in Faſhion; but the generality proceed but little further. The <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Vow</hi> is undertaken, as it ought, but by few; and thoſe that are <hi>Confirm'd</hi> are look'd upon with an odd Aſpect by the Vulgar, and thought more than ordinary Scrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. The Worſhip of God is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally neglected by ſome, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially performed by others, and Men
<pb facs="tcp:43329:7"/> think they have little Obligation to it beyond Decency, Cuſtom, and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Moſt of theſe nominal Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans live in a wilful <hi>Neglect,</hi> or rather <hi>Contempt</hi> of thoſe <hi>dear Pledges</hi> of our Salvation in the <hi>Lord's-Supper,</hi> and ſome abſtain from it (as they pretend) out of a prepoſterous fear of <hi>Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> There is an univerſal Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency as to our Duty, and a Coldneſs and Unconcernedneſs as to our future State. Religion has little or no Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over the Souls of Mankind, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige them to part with the leaſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Pleaſure for God's ſake, tho' the praiſe of Men, and other ſecular Advantages, ſometimes may. And no wonder, when the very Being of their <hi>Maker</hi> is impiouſly queſtioned by ſome, and <hi>Providence,</hi> that ſupports
<pb facs="tcp:43329:8"/> them, daily by others. <hi>Deiſm</hi> is breaking in upon reveal'd Religion; and, if that can prevail, <hi>Atheiſm</hi> will follow after: So that the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor'</hi>s Effort may be like his that would beautifie a falling Houſe, or dreſs up a dying Body: To all which he anſwers,</p>
            <p>1. That Religion (which was at firſt quick and active) naturally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cays, like the Courſe of a Stone or Bullet, the further it is remov'd from the firſt Principle that gave it Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And our Lord and his Apoſtles have foretold this decreaſe of Zeal, and a falling of many in the latter Days, and yet he remembers the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe for the Perpetuity of the Church, and <hi>that the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it;</hi> that is, that God by his mighty Power will
<pb facs="tcp:43329:8"/> preſerve its Being amongſt even thoſe many Adverſaries rais'd againſt it, by the Devil and the animal Life; ſo that there will ſtill be a competent Number of true and ſincere Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers. That there will and muſt be a <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> with whom he has promiſed to continue till the end of all Things, to direct and aſſiſt his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. 2. That there will be always Propriety and Inequality of Eſtates, and conſequently opportunities of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring to his Service. And, that the Support of thoſe dedicated to it, is, and ever will be (as it hath been) neceſſary to the continuance of it throughout all Times. That Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and ſuitable Returns of Praiſes will be ſtill a Duty incumbent upon all his Servants, and that God doth and will expect it: From all which
<pb facs="tcp:43329:9"/> it follows, that the Subject of theſe <hi>Papers</hi> are now, and will continue, ſeaſonable, even in the worſt of Times to come, (as well as in thoſe paſt) and are neceſſary to the Being of the Service of God, while the Church is <hi>Militant</hi> here on Earth.</p>
            <p>2. But (Secondly) if the whole Church ſhall not, (cannot fail) nor revealed Religion be thruſt out of the World, as the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> wou'd have it, yet 'tis the Opinion of many Perſons of different Intereſts, and the Deſires of ſome, That the Church in its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Conſtitution cannot continue long, and then who wou'd build a <hi>Piety</hi> upon ſuch a Foundation which is apt (through the Iniquity or Changeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Times) to fail? For then his pious Gift ſhall be either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by Covetouſneſs, (as we ſee
<pb facs="tcp:43329:9"/> many have) or elſe be diverted to the ſupport of a falſe Worſhip. The <hi>Author</hi> has taken notice of this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, and anſwered it as far as 'twas neceſſary to his Deſign: To which he has thus much to add; That 'tis confeſt, that this <hi>National Church</hi> has been long the Envy of ſome, as well as the Joy of others. That ſhe has Multitudes of ſecret E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies within her own <hi>Pale,</hi> as well as publick ones from without; yet hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto the Hopes of her Adverſaries have not prevail'd; but her Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, laid in the Blood of her <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> have ſtood immoveable. And, indeed, if we conſider the Purity of her Doctrines, the Reaſonableneſs of her Diſcipline, the Beauty of her Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Conformity of all to the Primitive State of God's Church in
<pb facs="tcp:43329:10"/> its Virgin Purity; yea, and to the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church of God, diſperſed over the whole World, (ſome few reform'd Churhces excepted, whoſe preſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Circumſtances will not admit of ſuch a Conſtitution; I ſay, if we conſider theſe things) it will be hard to conceive that this Church ſhould be totally overthrown as long as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Religion</hi> continues amongſt us; unleſs we ſuffer our ſelves to be over-run with <hi>Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſm,</hi> or conquer'd by the <hi>French,</hi> which I find we do not ſo dread, but that we dare ſtill purchaſe Eſtates, build, and plant here. And if any of our. Churches <hi>Ceremonies</hi> cou'd be chang'd for others of more Antiquity, Significancy, and Decency, ſhe wou'd yet be as much the ſame, as the ſame Woman in a different Dreſs. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb facs="tcp:43329:10"/> in this and all other Bequeſts to the Church, and to our own Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, we muſt referr our ſelves to that Providence that overſees and purvades all things, and no Man can undertake for <hi>Futurity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. But, <hi>Laſtly,</hi> it will be ſaid that theſe <hi>Papers</hi> cannot expect any ſucceſs in an Age wholly averſe to ſuch Doctrines. Men are generally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judic'd againſt any thing of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. They have more love for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves than to part with any thing to the <hi>Holy Church</hi> in their Lives<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, and more kindneſs to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations than to deprive them of that which they account their due at their Deaths. Theſe Doctrines (will they ſay) might have been harkned unto in the former Times of <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Ignorance,</hi> when the <hi>Prieſthood</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43329:11"/> carried all before it, and the Church had almoſt ſwallowed up the State. When Men bartered for Heaven with Earth, and thought to purchaſe an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate there with a <hi>religious Houſe</hi> here. But to hope to prevail with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Man at this time of the Day, to part with any thing upon the account of Religion, is to expect to cleave a Rock with a Word, and produce thence Rivers of Water. To this the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi>'s Anſwer is, That he cou'd well wiſh that every Man had a clear No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Value and Neceſſity of good Works, that he might not fall into the Extreams of <hi>Superſtition</hi> on the one ſide, or <hi>Profaneneſs</hi> on the other. For, as the firſt play'd the <hi>Tyrant</hi> in former Days, ſo, it is too plain, that the ſecond doth in the latter. That there ſhou'd be an equal poiſe
<pb facs="tcp:43329:11"/> betwixt Church and State, as there ought to be between <hi>Prerogative</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> and neither ſhou'd be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant. That tho' the Church here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore were once too rich (which yet was not ſo much the Church as an Excreſcency adhering to it) ſo as to make the Members of it too fat and idle, yet in many Places 'tis now ſo poor, that it is not able to attend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Divine Service. And, finally, tho' ſome are prejudiced againſt theſe Doctrines, yet they have no reaſon to be ſo, and there is great need of ſhewing them their Error; to which, he hopes, theſe <hi>Papers</hi> may contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute. And even in theſe laſt and worſt Days (to our Comfort, and the Glory of God be it ſpoken) Vertue and Piety are not without their <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries.</hi> There be ſtill many devout
<pb facs="tcp:43329:12"/> conſcientious Chriſtians, who can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt the right Uſe and Abuſe of Things, and ſee a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity for the Continuance of the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and the Maintenance of thoſe that attend it; to which they think that they are bound to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, and not wholly depend upon the Devotion of their ancient (without making up the Breaches and Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the Sacrilege of their more immediate) <hi>Predeceſſors.</hi> That the Number of theſe may increaſe, ſo that God may continue to be daily wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp'd, and his <hi>Miniſters</hi> encourag'd, ſupported, and maintain'd; and that every Pariſh or Congregation may not want an able and learned <hi>Paſtor</hi> to feed and inſtruct them, to pray for them, and conduct them in their way towards Heaven, is the Deſign of the
<pb facs="tcp:43329:12"/> 
               <hi>Author</hi> in theſe <hi>Papers;</hi> and having contributed what he could to this End, he leaves the Iſſue to him who only can give the Increaſe.</p>
            <p>I have only this to add, That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as theſe <hi>Papers,</hi> in their private ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, were only intended for the Service of a <hi>Perſon of Honour and Vertue,</hi> he is willing to relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh this his Right in them, and give them to the Publick, ſo that now every <hi>Intelligent Reader</hi> may claim a Title to them, as tho' they were his own, by a particular Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And the <hi>Author</hi>'s Prayer is, That they may go forth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper, to the moderating that cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, ingroſſing, and appropriating Humour, that ſeems to prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, both in our Lives and
<pb facs="tcp:43329:13"/> at our Deaths; that ſo God may be duly worſhipped, and Mankind mutually bleſs one another, under the auſpicious Influences of <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 12. l. 14. for <hi>Profeſſors</hi> read <hi>Poſſeſſors.</hi> p. 33. l. 12. for <hi>part r. put.</hi> ib. l. 13. dele <hi>it.</hi> p. 49. l. 24. for <hi>Juſtice</hi> r. <hi>Injuſtice.</hi> p. 77. l. 6. del. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. p. 99. l. 19. for <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>them.</hi> p. 118. l. 11. for <hi>Care</hi> r. <hi>Cure.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:43329:13"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE Firſt Diſcourſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>OF the difference of Eſtates, and the End of Providence therein,</hi> §. I.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Eſtates, and how commonly employed; with the beſt Account Men can commonly give of the ſame,</hi> §. II.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The End of theſe Papers, with the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Deſign and Apology,</hi> §. III.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>That we have no Title or Propriety in our Eſtates, in reſpect of God the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Donor,</hi> &amp;c. §. IV.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Ends for which God gives Men E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and what he expects from them,</hi> §. V.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Theſe Ends muſt be good, and are three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:43329:14"/>
               <item>I. <hi>Self-preſervation, what and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it conſiſts, with Cautions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon,</hi> §. VI.</item>
               <item>II. <hi>Good Works, Charity and Mercy,</hi> §. VII.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>This prov'd, 1. By the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and mutual dependance,</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>By the Law of God in the Holy Scriptures,</hi> §. VIII.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Objections anſwered,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>1. <hi>The pretence of Want, and not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any thing to ſpare,</hi> §. IX.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Law's Proviſion for the Poor: This prov'd to be no hinderance of Charity,</hi> §. X.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Several Inſtances of Methods of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; as Alms-Houſes, Schools,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the Colleges, and the two <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>That God hath not defin'd the</hi> Quota <hi>of Charity, conſidered and anſwered,</hi> §. XI.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How much is neceſſary to be imploy'd in Works of Charity,</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Summ of the Duty of Charity,</hi> §. XII.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Encouragements or Motives to Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> §. XIII.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:43329:14"/>
               <item>1. <hi>God deſigns it when he gives us Eſtates,</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>That Charity is a Complication of many excellent Graces.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That Charity doth not impoveriſh any Man, but tends to Riches and Increaſe,</hi> §. XIV.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>This prov'd, 1. By Scripture. 2. Reaſon. 3. Experience.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. <hi>That Charity is a generous and honourable Vertue,</hi> §. XV.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>That Charity is rewarded with Heaven as well as Earth,</hi> §. XVI.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The increaſe of its reward, noted,</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Concluſion: Shewing the difference betwixt the Deſert and Reward of the ordinary and charitable Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals,</hi> §. XVII.</item>
               <item>1. <hi>The ordinary diſpoſal of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates to our Heirs conſider'd, as to Happineſs, Deſert and Reward of the Teſtator,</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>That of the charitable Perſons: Inſtances in that of Founders and Benefactors of Colleges, Schools,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The preference in three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects,</hi> §. XVIII.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:43329:15"/>
               <item>1. <hi>He doth good to others as well as himſelf.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>He doth the beſt good in reſpect of the Body.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>His Works and Reward in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth till the end of the World,</hi> §. XIX, XX.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE Second Diſcourſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>VVHy the Author treats of Works of Piety in the laſt place,</hi> §. 1.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Aſſertion of this Diſcourſe; which is this, That every Man is bound, to the utmoſt of his Power, to promote the Honour of God, and maintain his Service. And (for the ſake of that) thoſe that officiate in the ſame, and that he that is able, and doth it not,
<pb facs="tcp:43329:15"/> miſ-imploys his Talent, and ſo muſt give an Account of that Neglect at the laſt Day,</hi> &amp;c. §. II.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What is meant by the Glory and Honour of God, or Divine Service.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>This exhibited, 1. By mediate Acts that tend to his Honour; as Moral and Natural Philoſophy. The Founders of Schools of Learning; and how their Societies tend to the Divine Service.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>By immediate Acts of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and what they be, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes of Men about it noted.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>That Works of Piety, and the Divine Service, ought to be promoted by our Eſtates. This proved in five Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions,</hi> §. III.</item>
               <item>Prop. 1. <hi>That God is to be worſhipped, and his Service promoted. Of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and inward Acts of Divine Worſhip, and that both are required. This prov'd from the Obligations we have to, 1. Truth. 2. Gratitude. And, 3. Indempnity or Pardon of Sin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Prop. 2. <hi>That God is daily to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped. Of publick and private
<pb facs="tcp:43329:16"/> Worſhip: And that one of theſe is to be offered up daily,</hi> §. IV.</item>
               <item>Prop. 3. <hi>That there is a neceſſity for a publick Miniſtry to perform the ſame,</hi> §. V.</item>
               <item>Prop. 4. <hi>That this Miniſtry ought to have a Competency, or ſufficient Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,</hi> §. VI.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What God himſelf heretofore aſſign'd for ſuch a Competency, 1. Amongſt the</hi> Patriarchs. 2. <hi>Amongſt the</hi> Jews; <hi>and the large Proviſions he made for them. 3. Amongſt the</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians: <hi>And how the Churches came to be endowed,</hi> §. VII.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How the Revenues of the Church came to be alienated,</hi> §. VIII.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Pretences and Methods of the ſame,</hi> §. IX.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The miſerable Effects of ſuch Alienati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> §. X.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Such as, 1. The Poverty of the Clergy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Their Contempt, and loſs of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> §. XI.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Their Depreſſion, and Dejection of Mind, and Converſation,</hi> §. XII.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:43329:16"/>
               <item>4. <hi>The increaſe of the Poor,</hi> §. XIII.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>The neglect and intermiſſion of the Service of God, and the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of its Indifferency and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſsneſs,</hi> §. XIV.</item>
               <item>6. <hi>Pluralities, and the Inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies thereof,</hi> §. XV.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The uſual Pleas for impoveriſhing of the Clergy, and the Objections againſt the Fourth Propoſition anſwer'd,</hi> §. XVI.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>What muſt be judg'd a Sufficiency for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Pariſh-Prieſt,</hi> ib.</item>
               <item>Prop. 5. <hi>That it is the Duty of every Chriſtian to provide ſuch a Competen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as far as he is able, for the Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Continuance of the Service of God,</hi> §. XVII.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>This demonſtrated from, 1. Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. 2. Example of God's Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in all Ages. 3. The Equity of the Thing, natural Reaſon, and Men of all Religions.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The ſeveral Pleas and Objections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Fifth Propoſition conſider'd and anſwer'd,</hi> §. XVIII.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A general and particular Application and Addreſs,</hi> §. XIX.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:43329:17"/>
               <item>1. <hi>To the Noble, Rich, and Wealthy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>To the Impropriators,</hi> §. XX.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>To thoſe that have no Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to provide for,</hi> §. XXI.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>To the Biſhops, Dignitaries, and others of the Clergy,</hi> §. XXII.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>To all Chriſtians in general: Wherein is ſhewed,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>1. <hi>The beſt Account that can be commonly made to God at the laſt Day, and its Inſufficiency,</hi> §. XXIII.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>A better way of accounting with God propos'd; and the Concluſion of the whole.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43329:17"/>
            <head>AN ESSAY TO Revive the Neceſſity OF THE <hi>Ancient Charity and Piety.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§. I. <hi>Of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Eſtates, and the End of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence therein.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat our bleſſed Lord ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd long ago concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the difference God makes in the diſtribution of his heavenly Talents, giving to ſome five, to others two, and to ſome one; is found true alſo of thoſe that are Earthly. Eſtates are now
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43329:18"/> (and ever have) been different in this World, and the Levelling Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple has been found as impracticable as it is unreaſonable. God gave at firſt (and ſince by his Providence continues) to ſome more, to others leſs, but to every one in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure a ſufficiency. Riches and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance (like other good Gifts) are from above, and ſo is the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement too; and tho' we ought to uſe a ſtudious Care, yet the Iſſue muſt be left to the Author. For our Experience will affirm the truth of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Adage; <hi>There is that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 11. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>ſcattereth and yet encreaſeth; and there is that withholdeth more than is meet, but it tendeth to poverty.</hi> As alſo that of the Apoſtle in a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sence; That <hi>it is not of him that planteth, nor of him that water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but of God to give the encreaſe.</hi> Thus Families and Eſtates have their (ſometimes unaccountable) riſe, continuance, and decreaſe. From mean Beginnings they ariſe to Greatneſs, and for a few Ages ſhine
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43329:18"/> like a Meteor and are admir'd, and then ſink like the ſame into their former obſcurity, and become ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct and unobſerv'd amongſt the Croud.</p>
               <p>This (worthy Sir) is a Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration uſeful in its kind, to put you in mind of your Houſe's Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality as well as your own; to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon and be thankful to that Power that has raiſed you up ſo far above others: Not to be proud and diſdain at thoſe that are paſs'd by, whilſt you are choſen to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Eſtate, but rather to fear, becauſe as your Eſtate is greater, ſo is your Charge and Duty, and ſo will your Account be. For to whomſoever much is given, of him much ſhall be required; and to whom Men have committed much, of him they will ask the more. That you be kind, loving, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municative to thoſe below you eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially (for Intereſt will oblige you to thoſe above) and like the Sun, warm and enliven every one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43329:19"/> the Sphere of your Activity, and that you wou'd live up to the End for which Providence deſign'd your Station; that is, that as you are rais'd up to a higher Capacity than others, ſo you would do more good than others. To apprehend truly what, and how much that Good is, it becomes you to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der two Things. <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Uſe that Men commonly put their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates to in this Age: And then, <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> The Uſe that God has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd them to put them to, and the Account that he expects of them accordingly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. II. <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Eſtates, and how commonly imployed, with the beſt Account they can give of the ſame.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If you, in the firſt place, take a view of the World, you will find that when a young Man begins to underſtand his Quality, and that he is born or deſign'd to an Eſtate above others, he begins to ſhake off his former Acquaintance, and thoſe that the ſtate of Childhood and Ignorance had render'd his Familiars, and to ſeek the Society
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43329:19"/> of his Equals in Birth and Fortune, and the Exerciſes that are proper to his Rank. He overlooks his old Companions, and will ſeldom (and that in private only) own that he knows them, and that which we below think to be a ſpice of Pride, is but neceſſary to his Place in the World, to conciliate to himſelf the Honour and Reverence due to him. When he hath found out a Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of his Joys and his Griefs, their great Care is to live up to the Character of their Houſes, and maintain the Honour of their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors. This is the Center to which all the Lines of the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, their Tables, Attendants, Equipage, Houſes, Gardens, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Appendages of Nobleneſs and Gentility do, and indeed ſhou'd tend. And this is true down from the Noble-man to the Farmer, and each Man in his ſeveral Degree aims at the Support and Credit of his Houſe and Family. For their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates; the Riotous waſte and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43329:20"/> them; the Covetous do what they can to hook in whatſoever comes within their reach; and the provident and good Husband, by his prudent management of what is left him, increaſes what he has, and finds an increaſe of Eſteem and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect proportionably. In fine, when every Man has acted his dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Part upon the Stage of this World, he ſettles it (or the Law for him) upon his Son or his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or his neareſt Relation. This is the Summ of the Life of Man; and the Account that he can give to his Maker in the other World muſt be accordingly. And the beſt that can be given, according to the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al management, is this: That they have husbanded their Charge to the beſt Advantage without fraud or oppreſſion, or wronging of any Man; and with the yearly Product thereof they have fed and cloathed themſelves, their Children, and their Servants. And beſides that, have maintain'd their State according
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43329:20"/> to their Degree, and have at ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Times gratified their Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites with ſuitable Pleaſures. This during their Lives; and that when they died they left their paternal Eſtate with Additions to their el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Sons, the preſumptive Heirs of their Dignities, together with ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Proviſions for their other Sons and Daughters. And in defect of ſuch Children, then to their Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews, or Nieces, or neareſt Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; or, in defect of theſe alſo (which is rare) to ſome of their Names, or whom they beſt fanſie. This (to paſs by the Extorſion and unjuſt Methods of Covetouſneſs, and thoſe profuſe and extravagant ones of Senſuality, not here to be named) is the beſt Account that uſually the beſt of Mankind can bring of what they have done here. But for any eminent Act of Piety, eſpecially for the Glory of God and the Advancement of his Service, either in their lives<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time or at their death, 'tis very rare
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43329:21"/> and extraordinary, and a Work of wonder, not imitation. 'Tis true, natural Compaſſion, Cuſtom and Credit obliges Men to give ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at their Gates; but then 'tis uſually the Superfluities of Life, and the Refuſe of their Tables, which otherwiſe wou'd ſtink and be corrupt; and at their deaths ſome will commend a ſmall Summ to the Poor to be diſtributed by their Executors, which is no ſooner received but ſpent: But, in theſe degenerate Times, how few ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Acts of Piety and Charity do we find as Monuments of our Love to God and our Neighbour? I wou'd not be thought to leſſen any Man's Charity when I ſay, that ſometimes a merciful and generous Nature, and (poſſibly Glory) may wring out of the Hands of our Heirs and Executors ſome good Remain. But then as it is rare, ſo it is thought a Work of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>errogation, not Duty; that which is laudable, but yet may be left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43329:21"/> without danger. And where is the Man that thinks ſuch Works neceſſary to Salvation? or, that God requires them, and they will be advantageous to us in another World? 'Twas otherwiſe in Times of yore, and not only Works of Charity but Piety were thought to be abſolutely requir'd of God, and therefore they cou'd not go out of the World without making a kind of Retaliation and Acknowledgment to God as well as Man; which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly was the Original of <hi>Deodands, Mortuaries,</hi> &amp;c. And a Will cou'd not be made without bequeathing God and his Church ſome Legacy. Hence it is they left us ſo many Monuments of both; but we their unworthy Poſterity have deſtroyed many, and think much to ſupport thoſe that remain. In a word, all that we can do is but to ſay, that we have ſerv'd the Neceſſities and Pleaſures of our ſelves, and them that are next to us in Relation; and, as for others we have done
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43329:22"/> them no good. And this we think ſufficient to juſtifie us before God and Man. But then may not a <hi>Scribe</hi> or <hi>Phariſee,</hi> or did not many of the good <hi>Heathen</hi> more than this? Or, is not this the Effect of the Law of Nature, which teaches me to love my ſelf, and do good only to my Friends and Relations, and is competible to the wickedeſt of Mankind? Is this the living up to the more perfect Law of Jeſus, which will ſometime try you with the ſorrowful Command of <hi>ſell all and give to the poor, and thou ſhalt have treaſure in Heaven?</hi> And which doth always oblige us to love even our very Enemy, and much more a poor peaceable Neighbour, and to watch opportunities to do good to all Men? Or, is Heaven a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for loving our ſelves, and for doing that which we cannot omit without violating our natural Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations? No, ſurely, The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion is a ſuper-addition of Duty as well as Promiſes and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43329:22"/> and therefore the ordinary Accounts of Mankind, concerning the diſtribution of their Eſtates, will not be allowed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§. III. <hi>The End of theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, with the Author's Deſign and Apology.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>To convince you of this great Truth, and to direct you to the due management of your Eſtate, ſo that you may be acquitted, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Reward of an <hi>euge bone Serve,</hi> &amp;c. is the Deſign of theſe Papers. And the rather, becauſe God hath given me (for Reaſons beſt known to himſelf) but a very ſhort Allowance; ſo that I can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be Exemplary nor Serviceable, as I deſire, in Works of Piety and Mercy, and mine own tyrannous Neceſſities wou'd fain engroſs all. I think it therefore my Duty to do what I can, tho' I cannot what I wou'd, and ſeek the Comfort of exciting others to do that which I am incapacitated to do my ſelf. And if God accepts the Will for the Deed, this will be a ſufficient Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. And this will the better
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43329:23"/> appear if you conſider the other Thing, which is to ſhew what God doth expect at our Hands in this Particular. And in order to this I will beg your Patience to diſcourſe of theſe two Things in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Of the Propriety and Title that every Man has to his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, in reſpect of God the Supreme Donor.</item>
                  <item>2. Of the End for which God hath given Eſtates, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently what he expects from the preſent Profeſſors.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. IV. That we have no Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, in reſpect of God the Supreme Donor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>1. Firſt then if we look for any Property or Title to our Eſtates, in reſpect of God, we ſhall find none. 'Tis true, every Man has a Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in what he poſſeſſes, in reſpect of his fellow-ſubject; and the Laws of God and Man, have declared a <hi>meum &amp; tuum,</hi> and fenced them from mutual encroachments. That is mine (in reſpect of my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43329:23"/> which I lawfully poſſeſs, whether by Inheritance, Gift, or Purchaſe. And this another Man ought not either to invade or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet. But 'tis otherwiſe in reſpect of God, our great Benefactor; who as he gives every one his <hi>Quota,</hi> ſo he ſaves to himſelf a Power of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it away; of transferring and changing, of raiſing and throwing down Men and Families. For <hi>the moſt high ruleth in the kingdom of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>Men, and giveth it to whomſoever he will; for his is the World and the fulneſs thereof.</hi> In him we live, move, and have our being, and he gives Life and Eſtate, and takes it away at his Pleaſure. When he actually interpoſes and declares his Will, all humane Laws are ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded. In that Caſe even killing is no murther, nor taking away Goods theft; as appears by the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s dealings with the Seven Nations in the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> and with the <hi>Egyptians</hi> at their departure out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Thus in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43329:24"/> the Goſpel he ſtrips the fooliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jector of all, when he takes his Soul away. <hi>Thou Fool, this night ſhall thy Soul be required of thee, and then whoſe ſhall thoſe things be which thou haſt provided?</hi> And as <hi>Job</hi> is the moſt celebrated Inſtance of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſo he is of the Inſtability of our Fortunes, and of God's diſpoſal of them. To day a Man the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt in Subſtance of all the Men in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and to morrow by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky Conſpiracy of deſign'd Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes meeting, or rather follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another, reduc'd to the State of a <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and the want of all things, Life only excepted: And, yet, after a time of Trial and patient Sufferance, reſtor'd by an extraordinary Providence, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with double to what he loſt. An Inſtance, not of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>price of Fortune, but the deſign'd Intrigue of Providence, and the Right God hath to give and take away; and ſo he made it in his ſelf-denying Hymn of Thankfulneſs.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43329:24"/> 
                  <hi>Naked came I out of Mother's womb, and naked ſhall I return: The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi> This is an Evidence that God is the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Lord, and may make a Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his own when he pleaſes, and that we are Tenants at Will, and no further.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, we call what we have, our own; and we transferr our Rights to others; but then 'tis only (<hi>quantum in nobis eſt</hi>) as far as we may. We give them a lawful Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion againſt our ſelves, and all that claim under us, but this is all but a humane and temporary Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; and can give no future Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity againſt the former Right of Providence. And when we die we divide our Acqueſts and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath them to our Children and Relations, and uſe the greateſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curities to entail it upon our Heirs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But all this (when the Supreme Owner pleaſes) in vain. For in a ſmall time Strangers ſhall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43329:25"/> feed in our Dining-Rooms, ſtretch themſelves on our Couches, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Fruits of our Labours, and the Pleaſures of our Buildings, Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and Contrivances. All this daily Experience confirms to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very conſidering Man, nor is it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by any that acknowledges a God and Providence. And I have us'd the more Words, not for the Doctrine but the Application's ſake; which is, That rich Men wou'd, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Be humble, and not carry themſelves with that extravagant Pride, as tho' they had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd it, or were to render no Account for it. That they wou'd, <hi>Secondly,</hi> Be grateful to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, and own him as their and our common Benefactor. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Be careful to manage their Truſt to the Intents and Purpoſes for which they were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: And what they are comes next to be diſcours'd of. And therefore,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>§. V. <hi>The Ends for which God gives Men E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and what he expects from them. Theſe Ends muſt be Good, and are three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:43329:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> As to the Intents of God in beſtowing Eſtates, you are to conſider: If God gives to ſome what he denies to others, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues to them and their Heirs what they call their own, it muſt be for ſome End, and that End muſt be the performance of ſome Good. For God doth nothing in vain, or for no End, and he propoſes no End but what is Good. Now all Good is ſuch in reſpect of three Objects; our Selves, our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and God, the chief Lord of all. There is no queſtion but God intends the Good of that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Perſon whom he makes Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer of his Talent: And thence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes ſelf-preſervation. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he cannot manage it himſelf without aſſiſtance, from Self-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation ariſes alſo that of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily and Dependants. But then God being an univerſal Father, and taking Care for all Mankind (which are his Family) equally, (tho he has not endow'd all equally)
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43329:26"/> thence ariſes a ſecond Good to our Neighbour, and eſpecially to thoſe that want any thing that he hath denied him and given us: That we may thereby exerciſe our Love and Charity, thoſe God-like Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues which are in him originally, and which he hath deriv'd to us, and expects we ſhou'd uſe towards one another. But then, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Tho' he is in himſelf ſo perfectly Happy, as to be incapable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any repletion from the Works of his Hands, yet to try our Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and renew in us a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his Benefits, he has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to himſelf a certain kind of Quit-Rent; and that is, that we ſhould not only acknowledge his Bounty to us publickly and private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but alſo contribute out of our Eſtates what is neceſſary, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſhould do ſo likewiſe: That his Supremacy and Goodneſs might be daily acknowledged by all, as it is daily received by all. From all which it follows, That no Man
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43329:26"/> is a ſole, abſolute, and free Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of his Eſtate, but that he is bound to Conditions of doing Good to himſelf and his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and the making of due returns of Gratitude to his God. That theſe are the Conditions of his Tenure, which (as it is at the Will of the Lord as to time, and may be ejected when he pleaſes, ſo) he ought during the ſpace of his poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion to perform the Conditions thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> pay his Quit-Rents, and do his Homage, upon the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties that will enſue thereon on the day of Enquiry and taking Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, when every Man ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive according to his Works. Thus much of the Ends in general; but I muſt conſider theſe three Uſes more particularly and ſeparately.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>§. VI. <hi>Of Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is the firſt End.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>1. And firſt of Self-preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the firſt End. That our Duty is to preſerve our Selves, our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Selves, our Offspring, which are our ſelves propagated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43329:27"/> and our Servants, which are kept for our Selves ſake, will not require many Words; for Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath imprinted it upon our Minds in Characters that be inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible: And this Principle is ſo fix'd and operative, that the only fear is, leſt it ſhould grow too faſt, to the ſtifling of the other. Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teaches us, that Self-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, like <hi>Moſes's</hi> Rod-Serpent, ready to ſwallow up the other two. Selfiſhneſs hath engroſs'd all, and Men look ſo much on themſelves, and their own Profits and Pleaſures, that they mind not their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, nor (what is more) their God. And therefore on this Head I muſt hold back the Hand, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what is due to our Selves and what not, leſt we ſhou'd cheat God and our Neighbour of theirs. There is no queſtion but there is due to our ſelves Neceſſaries, but what that is, is not defin'd, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of a Latitude according to our ſeveral Circumſtances in the World.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43329:27"/> 
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> There be Neceſſaries in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Life, ſuch as Food and Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: This is certainly allow'd us and our Dependents. 'Tis all the reaſon in the World, that in the ſweat of our Brows we ſhou'd eat our Bread, and wear thoſe Cloths that ſhould defend us in our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. <hi>Secondly,</hi> There be things neceſſary <hi>ad bene eſſe,</hi> to our well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being, as times and ways of Joy and Pleaſure: And therefore 'tis all the reaſon in the World, that God's Tenent reap the Comforts as well as the Troubles that he lays upon him under the Sun. That he eats his Bread with Joy, and drinks his Wine with a merry Heart then, when he hath Teſtimonies that God hath accepted his Labours; that then <hi>his Garments be white, and his Head lack no ointment.</hi> My mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, That at times of Feaſting he relax his Cares, and uſe ſuch Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities that are agreeable to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and the general Rules of Sobriety and Charity. <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:43329:28"/> There be Neceſſaries <hi>ratione perſonae &amp; conditionis unius cujuſque,</hi> things that are neceſſary to great Perſons and not to all. 'Tis all the reaſon in the World, that great Officers ſhou'd have great Attendants, and that high Stewards ſhou'd have a State anſwerable to their Places and Cares. The diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Men cannot be well mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted but by great Buildings, plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Tables, many Servants, and a Grandure becoming the Nobility and Gentry. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> There is a neceſſity <hi>ratione poſterum,</hi> a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Education, and a moderate Proviſion for their Children and Relations. The firſt ſort of Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity is abſolute, and muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd; the three other are capable of degrees, and muſt be us'd ſo far as agrees with Prudence and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, and the other two Ends that I am yet to ſpeak of. God nor Man will deny, but the Eſtate ſhall bear them all, if it can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Prejudice to God, our chief
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43329:28"/> Lord, or our Neighbour. But he that ſpends all on himſelf and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, ſo that he can allow God and Charity nothing, is like (nay is) a Tenant that waſtes all on his Luxury, and ſo can pay no Rent. If Eſtates will not maintain us as we wou'd, they muſt as they can; and we muſt cut off ſome of our vain Expences to ſecure the main Point. We make it a Rule, that when Taxes run high, and our Crop is but ſmall, Expences are to be retrench'd, that we may pay our Rents: And why in a greater Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern ſhould we not abate ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from our extraordinaries for God and Charity's ſake? Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries we all muſt have, (but they are but a few) but the Appendages of Honour and Greatneſs may be encreaſed or diminiſhed according to the Circumſtances of Time and Place, without ſinning againſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This will not ſeem hard to him that conſiders how much may be par'd off from Vanity without
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43329:29"/> diminution of Honour, and that if our unneceſſary (not to ſay ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) Expences were ſav'd, and put into the Box of Charity, it wou'd be fill'd and run over. For I have obſerv'd amongſt all ſorts of Men, high or low, rich or poor, they will ſpend liberally upon the ſcore of Friendſhip and Company at home or abroad, and are aſham'd to ſhow any reluctance at it; but when a ſmall piece of Charity is to be done, or but a <hi>Brief</hi> to be given to, how many Difficulties are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, and what Complaints for want of Money! And yet at the ſame time if an uſeleſs Piece of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is propos'd to ſale, or ſome little thing to gratifie Oſtentation, how eager they are, and how will they incommode themſelves to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Money to purchaſe it! And yet, when procur'd, it ſhall be laid up in a Box, and there ſleep (it may be) whole Years together, and never ſee the Sun. How happy wou'd it be if thoſe Jewels were
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43329:29"/> imploy'd to adorn the Soul withal, and if thoſe precious Stones were turned into Bread for the Poor! If thoſe Pearls were diſſolv'd into Drink for them! But this muſt not be hop'd for; yet I muſt ſay again, That many of theſe chargeable Trifles may be ſpar'd without the leaſt diſhonour. And here I will not be ſo impudent as to ranſack the Ladies Cloſets, and ſearch their Boxes, and note their Extravagances in Dreſſings and outward Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nor will I compute the Charge of their Lordſhip's ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerary Hawks, Hounds, Horſes, Attendants; and the Inſtruments of State and Pleaſure of both Sexes. They are able to judge of that beſt; as alſo what may be ſpared without detriment to Life or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; for ſomething muſt be, if the Eſtate will not bear it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: For both God and Man will expect Works of Charity and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to be done while we are here, and that in proportion to what
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43329:30"/> we poſſeſs. And this I name in the Second Place, as an End for which God has given us our Earthly Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and which is next to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>§. VII. <hi>The ſecond End, Works of Charity and Mercy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>2. That no Man's Eſtate is ſo much his own, that he may ſpend it as he pleaſes, and that our dear Country, our Neighbour, our Friend, yea and our Enemy (if in want) claims a part of it; and that God will expect an Account of theſe Things at the great Audit, appears by the Book of Nature, as well as by the Holy Scriptures, and hath the united Suffrage of Reaſon and Religion.</p>
               <p>In Nature we find that as every<note place="margin">This prov'd firſt, By the Law of Nature.</note> thing depends, ſo every thing is ſubſervient to each other; and the Univerſe preſerves it ſelf by mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Helps and Aſſiſtances. The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens rowl about inceſſantly for the Benefit of thoſe things within their Vortex; and the Sun, the greater Luminary, rejoycerh as a Giant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh'd
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43329:30"/> with Wine, to run his Courſe, (as <hi>David</hi> expreſſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, according to Vulgar appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion;) or, rather, (according to the Modern Sages in Nature) ſtands ſtill in the Centre, and contents himſelf to ſend out his Emanations of Light and Heat to gild the Globes that wheel round about him, and enliven the Creatures that inhabit them. The Earth, our common Mother, feeds and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports her Offspring; and they, in return, enrich her Superficies. The ſenſible Creatures, notwithſtanding the mutual enmity of ſome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Food one to another, and ſubmit to the Law of Nature, and ſerve and feed Man, the Lord of the viſible Creation. And God hath convinc'd Man by the Wants that he is ſenſible of, and the Help he expects from others, to ſupply theirs alſo. To give, as well as ask, and to be a bleſſing to thoſe from whom he expects a bleſſing: For no Man can live without the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43329:31"/> of another; and the King is beholden to the Charity of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in his Childhood, and the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of the Field throughout his whole life. To which I add, That the End of the Exiſtence of Things is founded in Community; and we live not for our ſelves, but for ſome Being without us. The Sun ſhines not to it ſelf, but to us; and the Earth feeds and nouriſheth not her ſelf, but the Creatures that live upon her. The Birds, Beaſts, and Fiſhes continue their Species, but it is for the delight and ſervice of Man. And Man was not made to eat and drink, and propagate his like, but to be ſerviceable to his God, and his fellow-Creatures. Is not this then the Leſſon of Nature, and do not we read it in all the Works of God; That Self-preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is not the ſole End of the created Beings, but the Good of the Community, as the Glory of God is that of the whole Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>§. VIII. <hi>And, 2dly, By the Law of God in the Holy Scripture.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:43329:31"/>
               <p>But if the Book of Nature be ſeal'd up to thoſe that will not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen or read it, yet the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are not ſo; that Book lies open, and is read and expounded daily in our Ears, and (if we do not ſtop them) we cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of our Duty; and this whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we conſider God's Commands about Works of Charity in the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> or the <hi>New.</hi> In the <hi>Old</hi> he was pleas'd to ſettle an Eſtate by a poſitive Law on the Poor, <hi>viz.</hi> A Second Tenth (after that of the <hi>Levites</hi> was paid) every Third Year; which was the Third Part of every Man's Nine Parts, (the Tenth being paid before to the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites;</hi>) and beſides this, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Gleanings of the ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered Corn; the reſtoring of the Pledge; and lending without In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and other occaſional Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Add to theſe, thoſe general acts of Love, which we are taught to bear even to our Enemy, whoſe Oxen or Aſſes (and conſequently
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43329:32"/> any other of his Goods) we ſhould not ſuffer to fall into any hazard, and much leſs his Perſon: So that here is a manifeſt Charge entail'd for ever upon every <hi>Jews</hi> Eſtate for the good of the Publick. And this is greater to the Chriſtians, if you conſider that our bleſſed Lord not only fill'd up the Vacuities, but ſtrain'd up the Obligations of their Law higher than it was before. <hi>Give,</hi> ſaith our Lord, <hi>to every one</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 5. 42.</note> 
                  <hi>that asketh thee; and from him that would borrow, turn thee not away. Love your very Enemies, and do good to them that hate you.</hi> Thus he for all: And then for our Friends, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will teach us enough for them. So that the Law of Chriſt ſubjects our Eſtates to a boundleſs and univerſal Charity, even to the worſt as well as beſt of Men; and no Man that wants muſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted or neglected. And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> accordingly orders his<note place="margin">Gal. 6. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Galatians</hi> to watch opportunities to do good to all Men; and to the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43329:32"/> Houſhold of Faith eſpecially. And leſt this doing Good ſhou'd be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted of a verbal Benefaction, of wiſhing them well, and praying<note place="margin">Jam. 2. 20.</note> for them only, St. <hi>James,</hi> another of his Apoſtles, vehemently declaims againſt ſuch Charity, and calls it a <hi>dead work,</hi> and the Man vain that truſts to it. And this was no more than what he had learn'd from his Maſter in the inſtructive Parable he made in anſwer to the Queſtion of the Lawyer, Τίς ἐστίν μου πλησίον <note place="margin">Luke 10.</note> 
                  <hi>who is my Neighbour?</hi> Where he ſhews by the ſequel, that 'tis our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to engage our Time, Beaſt, Purſe, and Credit, for the ſake of a wounded and wanting Enemy, Stranger, or Unbeliever. For ſo did the Charitable <hi>Samaritan</hi> to the wounded <hi>Jew,</hi> he <hi>bound up his wounds, pouring in oil and wine;</hi> he <hi>ſet him on his own Beaſt, brought him to his Inn;</hi> paid for his paſt Charge, and engag'd for his future. Who cou'd do more for his Friend and neareſt Relation? This Nature and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43329:33"/> Gratitude teaches us, but the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion extends it to the moſt hated of Men. For ſo ended our Saviour that Parable; <hi>I tu, &amp; fac ſimiliter; Go thou and do like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</hi> And finally, to ſhew the neceſſity of Works of Charity, our Lord has declared in his Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the laſt Judgment, That no leſs than Heaven is the Reward (and no leſs than Hell the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Neglect) of Charity.</p>
               <p>Thus if we conſider what God hath declared, either under the Law or under the Goſpel, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not queſtion but that God, the rightful <hi>Proprietor</hi> of all Things, hath conveyed our Eſtates to us, clog'd with the Incumbrance, or rather Duty, of giving Part to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Uſes; and that every Man is no more than a Truſtee for what he poſſeſſes, for ſeveral Uſes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and limited by the general Rules of Charity: And finally, that a ſtrict Account will be exacted of us about the ſame at the laſt Day,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43329:33"/> and that under the higheſt Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Rewards and Puniſhments. This being ſo, what I have more to ſay upon this Head, ſhall be divided in anſwering the Objections that Men make to excuſe themſelves from Works of Charity, and in ſhewing how great Encouragements and Obligations there are to this Duty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>§. IX. <hi>Objections anſwer'd.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>1. Firſt therefore for the Excuſes they wou'd appear extream fooliſh and light, did not Selfiſhneſs part it it ſelf in the Scale. Such is this which follows; and that is,</p>
               <div type="objection_answered">
                  <head>Obj. 1. <hi>The pretence of Want an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p> 1. The pretence of Want. There is not enough for our ſelves and the Neceſſities of our Dependants, and therefore Charity muſt begin at home; where ſhe ſhall find too much Work ever to go abroad. But this Plea is generally falſe, and the effect of an evil Eye. We look upon our Eſtates through falſe Opticks, and 'tis worth our Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to ſee how our ſeveral Vices
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43329:34"/> delude us. Pride and Oſtentation preſents them to us through a Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying Glaſs, and makes us boaſt of more than we have. But when any good Work deſires entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Covetouſneſs and ill Nature preſently turns the other end of the Glaſs, and repreſents our Eſtate ſmall, and far off, and ſo furniſhes us with a Plea of Inability; which yet we wou'd ſcorn any Body elſe ſhou'd make for us. Here's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for you, (ſay thoſe within Doors,) but if thoſe without ſhou'd ſay ſo much, 'twou'd be taken as no mean Affront. But Selfiſhneſs is impudent, as well as inſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and, like the Daughters of the Horſe-Leach, always crys <hi>Give, give.</hi> And to <hi>Agar</hi>'s four Things I may add a fifth that never has enough; and that is, Covetouſneſs. And yet, perhaps, this Plea may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times be admitted as true, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver as concluſive. We have ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom enough, in compariſon of what we wou'd have. We have not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43329:34"/> to ſatisfie our Luſts and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, our Pride and vain Glory. We ask Counſel of our Fears and Deſires, our Pleaſure and Delights, and then 'tis no wonder that we are anſwer'd, That there is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. We take falſe Meaſures in our Allowances; and our Miſery and Folly is, that we cannot be ſatisfied without much more than we really need. We conſult either Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs or Prodigality in ſtating our Wants, which are Counſellors both clamorous and inſatiable. Our Stables and Tables are commonly too large for our Houſes; and our Houſes for our Eſtates; and all of 'em not large enough for our Minds; and when we have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd one Accompliſhment, we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently want another; and our Wants increaſe the more they are repaired, and ſtill as one thing is done another ſtarts up and pleads to be rectified: And thus poor (or rather noble) Mortals are amus'd and abus'd all their Life long; flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43329:35"/> with Expectations, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by Fruition, and all this to keep off the Complaints of Piety and Charity, and hinder themſelves of Happineſs! And beſides our ſelves (which as things are mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged take up our whole time) there be Sons and Daughters, Nephews and Nicces, Grand-Children, and (ſometimes) a numerous Poſterity to be provided for, that they (too) may live in Affluence and Vanity, when we have acted our Parts on the Stage, and are gone off. Why if all this, and whatſoever Fancy or Luxury can propoſe, be firſt done before you can bethink your ſelf of doing any thing upon the Score of Vertue and Religion, the Wealth of <hi>Croeſus</hi> wou'd be inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, and the Age of <hi>Methuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> too ſhort for you. Pride and Vanity are Vices both chargeable and importunate! But if we wou'd but once bound our Deſires, and limit our Wiſhes; if we wou'd but pare off our Excreſcencies, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43329:35"/> learn to deny our ſelves ſome things which we muſt, and other things which we ought to want here, we then might find ſomething to ſpare for other Uſes than what ſerves our ſelves. Let our unreaſonable Gaie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Ornaments be leſs ſtudied, and vain Expences at Gaming, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot, and Luxury be ſaved, and what is laid up as uſeleſs be produc'd, and there wou'd be a Stock ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for the Exerciſe of Charity. God will be contented with that which we ſacrifice to our Luſts and Appetites. Deal ingenuouſly with him, and let not the deceitful Heart cheat him of that, and perhaps it will be enough. This may ſerve to baffle this Pretence, which might be ſufficiently anſwer'd by ſaying only this; As Self-preſervation is neceſſary, ſo are Works of Piety and Charity; and if the Soul is more excellent than the Body, and the Life to come more to be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued than that which is preſent; if Eternity is to be preferr'd before
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43329:36"/> Time, and a never-ending Reign in the Regions of Light and Bliſs be more deſirable than this ſhort and uncertain abode in a Vale of Darkneſs and Sorrows; then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Controverſie, the Duties of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Charity are more neceſſary even than Self-preſervation: For this prolongs a miſerable Life, but Charity and Piety enſures a Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without mixture of Alloy or fear of Change. And therefore tell me no more that you have not enough. You may (nay you muſt) find ſufficiency for all three. Nor is this directed only to the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Gentry, to the Great, Rich, and Fortunate, but to all; for Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is in every Man's Power more or leſs, and the meaneſt may find opportunities to exerciſe it. Even the pooreſt may meet Offices in which he may be ſerviceable to the richeſt, as the Mouſe (in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) was to the Lion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>§. X. Obj. 2. <hi>The Laws Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for the Poor anſwer'd.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:43329:36"/>
               <p>2. But it will be further obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; That the Law hath plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully provided for the Poor; that they are ready to be our Maſters, having a ſufficient Part of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates ſettled upon them; and that upon Complaint they may have poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of whit is their due without delay or charge; ſo that no Men need to want but ſuch as are idle, and that 'tis even a Sin to relieve theſe. And further, That it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry difficult to give any Charity but what will eaſe the Rich, and that they (not the Poor) will have the Benefit of it. That Gifts are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly abuſed; that the Intentions of the Donor are ſoon perverted, and that ſuch Donations are uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Injury to the Publick. And that finally, the Object of Charity being taken away, the Duty cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. To all which I anſwer in their order.</p>
               <p>1. For the hardneſs of our Hearts theſe Laws were made, and it is no great Commendation to us that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43329:37"/> there was a neceſſity for them. It ſhews at leaſt that this is the <hi>Iron Age,</hi> wherein all the Bonds of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion were broken, and Heaven and Hell laid aſide; ſo that our <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlators</hi> were forc'd to make uſe of the more powerful Secular Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to prevent the miſerable periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our Streets.</p>
               <p>2. But, <hi>Secondly,</hi> This Objection ſtands upon a falſe Suppoſition, that only the old and decrepit, and ſuch as come within the compaſs of the Law, are Objects of Charity; and whereas there be as many (or more) that receive no Collection, are ſuch then thoſe that do? There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny poor laborious Houſe-keepers, that hunger and thirſt in ſecret, and are aſham'd to make their Wants known, and yet help to maintain thoſe that want leſs than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: Theſe may well exerciſe our Conſideration and Mercy. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Prediction has been hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to verified, and we have (and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall have) thoſe with us whoſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43329:37"/> Wants will keep alive the Fire of Charity, beſides thoſe that the Laws have provided for. There be ſeveral occaſional Acts of Mercy that meet us every Day; ſuch are the Relief of the diſtreſſed, the Comfort of the afflicted, the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of thoſe that are wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſlandered, the ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the weak Hands, and the confirming the feeble Knees. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe of durable Effects, ſuch are, the erection, endowing, or aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting of Habitations for poor Widows and the Fatherleſs; a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue contrary to the <hi>Phareſaick</hi> way of devouring them. The Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Youth, and placing out of poor Children unto fit Trades and Callings. Children are the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive Supports of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth when we are gone: And therefore to take Care of the form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Manners, and the mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and perfecting of their Natures, is an ineſtimable Good to Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and a probable Way of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43329:38"/> many Souls to Heaven. And, that I may not mention any more, look but upon the many Charities in <hi>London</hi> and elſewhere, and you'll find more ways to exerciſe this Chriſtian Vertue than I fear will be uſed.</p>
               <p>And here I cannot chuſe but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, and at the ſame time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate Mankind for all the <hi>Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries</hi> of Learning and Religion, and eſpecially for the glorious Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations in the two Univerſities of our Land, founded and augmented <hi>by Men and Women famous in their Generations.</hi> For, if we conſider their lofty Buildings, regular Walks, pleaſant Gardens; their Chappels, Halls, and Libraries; the Gravity and Learning of their Superiors, and the Civility and Obedience of the Inferiors, and (in a word) the Decency and Symmetrical Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Edifices, or Vertues of thoſe that now are ſo happy as to inhabit them, we muſt ſay, That hardly all the World can equal
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:43329:38"/> the one, and all Ages the other. Here Pleaſure and Profit, Wit and Ingenuity, all the Graces, and all the Muſes have their peaceful and innocent Habitation. And tho' ſome (overcloy'd with the beſt things) leave theſe Seats for a noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie World; yet none did ever ſo, but (as he had cauſe enough) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented him of it afterwards. Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not that I mention theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Inſtances of Charity. So they are, and ſo they were at firſt intended; and not (without offence be it ſpoken) for thoſe that are Rich, Great, and have ſufficient Eſtates to maintain their Relations there, (and who yet baſely covet and procure the Founders Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) but for the meaner ſort; ſuch I mean, to whom Nature hath been liberal in the Gifts of the Mind, but ſcanty in thoſe of Fortune: That theſe as well as others might find means to emerge out of their obſcurities, and grow up into Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; that they might exerciſe and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:43329:39"/> improve their Talents to the Glory of God, the Honour of his Church, and the Good of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weal. All theſe were the Effects of a pious Charity, or a charitable Piety; or, rather, of Piety and Charity united; and, if no where elſe, yet there you may find op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of adding to both. But this more naturally falls under the Third End; of which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. And therefore to return.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> 'Tis not the Poor alone, but every Man that may be the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſional Object of Liberality. The wounded <hi>Jew</hi> was not poor before he was robbed, otherwiſe he might have paſs'd on ſafely; and the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan</hi> that aſſiſted him in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity might have been in the ſame Condition himſelf: <hi>Time and Chance happens to every Man,</hi> and none are free from the Misfortunes of this unconſtant World. 'Tis our Duty to be in a readineſs to aſſiſt the afflicted, and God only knows whoſe turn ſhall be next ſo.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:43329:39"/> Thoſe into whoſe Minds God hath put good Deſires, ſhall have ſome opportunities to bring the ſame to good Effect. We cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Objects of Charity, if we have ſincere Intentions to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>§. XI. Obj. 3. <hi>That God hath not defin'd the</hi> Quota <hi>of Charity, anſwer'd.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>3. Laſtly, it is ſaid, That if Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality muſt have a ſhare of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, over and above what the Law obliges us to, it ſhall yet have little enough. For God nor Man hath defin'd the <hi>Quota</hi> of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundant Charity. I may give what I pleaſe, and where. And I know my own Wants, and do not thoſe of others, and therefore I think it beſt to adminiſter to mine own Neceſſities, (which ought to be firſt ſerv'd) and then to thoſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (if I have ought to ſpare) and not otherwiſe: For if God hath not appointed what Part of my Eſtate I ſhou'd beſtow upon Works of Charity, then 'tis left to my ſelf; and if ſo, <hi>Self</hi> muſt be firſt ſatisfied, and then there will be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:43329:40"/> but little left: So that this is the way to conſtitute a partial Judge, who will ſhrink up the Portion of Charity to a very ſmall quantity. To which I anſwer:</p>
               <p>1. 'Tis confeſſed, That neither the particular Modes, nor the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of doing Good, are (or indeed can be) defin'd, preſcrib'd, and enforc'd under a Penalty; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they depend upon future Contingencies, and God deals with Man as with an ingenuous Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. He loves a free-will Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and therefore has left us a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. He has not ſet the Bounds and Limits, becauſe we might ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance it according as we find op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity. But then if any Man from thence takes occaſion to ſhrink it up to that minuteneſs that it is next to nothing; let him know, that he doth but cheat himſelf of his Reward, as well as God and his Neighbour of their Due. For the general Rules of loving (<hi>viz.</hi> ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectively, and to all the purpoſes of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:43329:40"/> Good) our Neighbour as our ſelves, will oblige us to imploy a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Part of our Eſtates in that Duty. The Rule of doing Good to all Men will oblige us to act as far as we are able; and how far that is, God knows better than we do our ſelves, nor can we think to deceive him. He ſees the true ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of Self-preſervation, and what that doth require, what we may ſpare, together with the Thoughts of our Hearts and the Sincerity or Hypocriſie of our Intentions, and will reward us accordingly.</p>
               <p>2. Tho' God hath not defin'd what Proportion he expects for the Uſes of Piety and Charity, yet we may well take an eſtimate of that by what he appointed to the <hi>Jews,</hi> his old People; for the hardneſs of whoſe Hearts he thought it beſt to preſcribe particulars. And that was, every third Years ſecond Tythe, which was the thirtieth Part yearly; <hi>The gleanings, the reſtoring of the pledge, and borrowing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:43329:41"/> uſe,</hi> &amp;c. This was the ſettled Proportion of Charity, and it was a <hi>Jews</hi> Righteouſneſs, (<hi>Deut.</hi> 24. 13.) That Duty which he was bound to do in Righteouſneſs or Juſtice; and without the doing of which he cou'd not be accounted a juſt or righteous Perſon. For this was the Poors due, which they might demand by Law, and which it was Injuſtice to deny them. But beſides this, there was a higher De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Charity; which was, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt them on all Occaſions, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all manner of acts of Kindneſs to them over and above what the Law preſcrib'd. And this was the natural Effects of loving their Neighbours as their ſelves. The aſſiſting and providing for a woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Man on the Way, as the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan</hi> did for the <hi>Jew</hi> he found be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Jericho, Luke</hi> 10. The extraordinary and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſional Acts of Pity were called Mercy or Goodneſs, and the Man that us'd them was call'd a good
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:43329:41"/> Man. Thus a righteous Man and a good Man ſeem'd to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd. The latter of more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert<note place="margin">Rom. 5. 7.</note> than the former. <hi>Scarcely for a righteous Man</hi> (one that is juſt and gives every Man his legal due and no more) <hi>will one die; tho' perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture for a good Man</hi> (the chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Perſon, who obliges Mankind by all manner of extraordinary Kindneſs) <hi>ſome would even dare to die.</hi> Poſſibly there may be found ſome Perſon that out of Gratitude, and the deſire of continuing ſuch a common Bleſſing to Mankind, wou'd lay down his Life for to redeem his. Thus in <hi>Micah</hi> 6. 8. God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires us firſt (as the loweſt Duty) <hi>to do juſtly;</hi> and then, ſecondly, (as a higher Perfection) <hi>to love Mercy;</hi> and then, thirdly, (as the higheſt) <hi>to walk humbly with our God.</hi> And <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> is exhorted by <hi>Daniel to break off his Sins</hi> (of Juſtice, Pride, <hi>&amp;c.) by righteouſneſs,</hi> (by doing juſtly, and making reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>&amp;c.) and his iniquities,</hi> (of Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:43329:42"/> and Tyranny) <hi>by ſhowing Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to the Poor,</hi> &amp;c. This being ſet laſt, as a higher Perfection than the firſt. Finally, where we read ελεη<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>μοσύνη, Alms, in our Saviour's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<note place="margin">Matth. 6. 1.</note> on the Mount, ſome ancient Copies have it δικαιοσύνη, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And ſo the Vulgar <hi>Latin</hi> at this Day reads it; <hi>Attendite ne ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiam veſtram faciatis coram homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus; See that ye do not your Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or Righteouſneſs before Men.</hi> So that a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Righteouſneſs (which was the paying of the ſettled Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to the Poor) was, as to Degrees deſcending, limitted; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low which they might not ſink: But the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Mercy or Charity ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded that, and was not limitted as to Degrees aſcending. It was ſomething above Righteouſneſs, and exceeding it; but how much, was left to Zeal joyn'd with Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to determine. Now all this is only to give Light to the Place of our Saviour, <hi>Matth. 5. 20. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept your righteouſneſs exceed the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:43329:42"/> righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, ye ſhall in no caſe enter into the kingdom of God.</hi> Which thus underſtood teaches us, That Chriſt expects, that we ſhou'd at leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> in our Liberality to the Poor, and that our Works of Mercy ought to exceed theirs; that God expects a higher <hi>Quota</hi> from the Chriſtian than he did from the <hi>Jew,</hi> in proportion to the greater Grace and Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that he hath received under the Goſpel. This being laid down for a Principle, the reſt is left to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man's Circumſtances, and to the Rules of Prudence, only with the Apoſtle's Caution, 2 <hi>Cor. 9. 6. He that ſoweth ſparingly ſhall reap ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>§. XII. <hi>The Summ of this Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And now having, I think, fully ſilenced theſe importunate Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, give me leave (Sir) out of the Premiſes to conclude our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be this; That all Men watch all opportunities of mutual Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:43329:43"/> and Kindneſs, but the Rich eſpecially, as having more Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience and Power to do Good, and from whom God will without doubt expect an Account accordingly. Spend not therefore all upon your Self and Attendants, nor let your Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and Appetites engroſs all. Charge your ſelf every Year with ſome publick or private Good, more or leſs according to your Ability, and when the Year is ended, be able to give God and your own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence an Account of it. Put not off Charity till your death, and then think it enough if your Executors give ſomething at your Funeral; which uſually turns to little Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. 'Tis a ſign of an earthly and ſenſual Mind to part with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing while you are able to keep it; and 'tis no Thanks to give what we can keep no longer. While we live our Charity cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, but when we are gone it may. Tho', by the way, it is no loſs to us, for God rewards accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:43329:43"/> to our good Intentions, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Effects they may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally produce; and 'tis not the Iniquity of Mankind in abuſing Gifts of Piety, that ſhall rob the Donor of his Crown. Let us do Good, and truſt God with the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue. This I note here, having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got to anſwer the latter part of the ſecond Objection in its place <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 39.</note>. But altho' I wou'd have every Man's Charity begin in his life-time, yet I wou'd not have it end with it. The more durable it is, the more glorious and beneficial; it the longer preſerves the Fame of the Founder, and is an increaſe of his Happineſs, by how much his Gift continues to do Good to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. It gathers Strength and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue by its Age. It is the beſt Tomb and Epitaph, and therefore, <hi>Conde tibi tumulum, nec fide haeredis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mori,</hi> &amp;c. Build up your Pillar your ſelf, and ſee (if poſſible) your Work finiſhed; for there is no Work, nor Device, nor Wiſdom in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:43329:44"/> the Grave, whither we are all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>§. XIII. <hi>The Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements to Charity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Having ſaid thus much in ſettling the Duty I plead for, and directing it, there remains that I ſhould ſpeak of the Encouragements we have to it, of which I have made (Sir) my ſelf your Debtor: And, among the many that may offer themſelves to your view, let theſe Three have a particular Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p>1. Then 'tis very probable that<note place="margin">1. <hi>God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns Works of Charity when he gives E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates.</hi>
                  </note> God Almighty deſigned this End when he fitted you for the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an Eſtate, and gave you an Eſtate to manage. Some End he had in joyning you together, (and may it be long before this Tye is diſſolved) and that was Good. This Good muſt be either the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of your Self and Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants in particular, or the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being of your Fellow-Mortals alſo. The firſt is a good thing, but the ſecond added to it makes it more
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:43329:44"/> excellent. And God, without all doubt, aim'd at that End which was moſt Noble: And that this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is ſuch, will appear if you conſider that the exerciſe of Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality is the exerciſe of many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and precious Graces together, in one and the ſame Act. <hi>Firſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">That Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is a Complica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent Graces.</note> 'Tis an Act of ſelf-denyal, in which I take away ſomething from my ſelf to give to another: For Nature wou'd engroſs all to it ſelf if it cou'd receive it; and has an Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite to all the good Things we poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs, tho' we are convinc'd we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not uſe them. He that parts then with ſome good Thing to his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour denies himſelf the ſame; and, conſequently, acts upon a higher Principle than that of Nature. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> 'Tis a preſent ſubmiſſion to the Will of God that has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me ſo to do, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, a preference of his Will to my own. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> 'Tis an Act of Faith and Truſt in him, that he is able to preſerve me without this
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:43329:45"/> I part with, or to provide it for me when I want it. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> 'Tis an Earneſt, That I ſhall part with all, if he commands it, as willingly as I do this for his ſake. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> 'Tis a free-will Offering to the Poor for his ſake, and an acknowledgment that I receive all from him. <hi>Sixth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> And laſtly, 'Tis an Antidote to that Depraver of the Mind and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy both, that unreaſonable, poor, ſlaviſh, and diſtruſtful Root of all Evil, Covetouſneſs. And now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and judge (Sir) how vaſt a difference there is betwixt Charity to your ſelf and to others, Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſervation and doing Good to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men. The firſt is from Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the ſecond from Grace. That's Self-love, this is the Effect of the love of God. That complies with the Root (and conſequently Branches) of all Evil, this oppoſes it. That may be the Act of the greateſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and wickedeſt Man in the World; this (if conſcientiouſly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd for God's ſake) muſt be
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:43329:45"/> that of a Child of God. And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, That is rewarded by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent enjoyments of this Life only, (which God knows are very few and inconſiderable) but this brings forth ſome preſent Fruit, and that not to be deſpiſed, (as I ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently obſerve) and after tends to a joyful Eternity. Beſides, Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſervation may be attain'd with Neceſſaries only, and beſt by them. Superfluities uſually tend to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of Nature. And God wou'd never have beſtowed theſe upon you for the End, for which they are neither adapted themſelves, neither are either uſeful or uſed. They are more than is neceſſary to you, but others want them, and therefore they were given for their Uſe, and not for your own. I mean, for the exerciſe of Charity and other good Graces that God delights to ſee us perform; <hi>With ſuch Sacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi> From all which it is evident, That Works of Charity and Mercy are one End why God
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:43329:46"/> has beſtowed his Largeſs upon Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: <hi>And he that is wiſe will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe things, and underſtand the loving kindneſs of the Lord.</hi> Now if this was one of God's Ends, (as it needs muſt be) you rob God of his due, when you deny Charity hers; you live beſide the End to which Providence hath directed you; you miſimploy your Eſtate, and will be call'd to an Account for the contempt of God, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing his Creatures: So that as good Works are your End, they are your Intereſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>§. XIV. <hi>That Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity doth not impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſh us, but tends to increaſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>2. A ſecond Encouragement is this, That Works of Charity is your temporal Advantage. And here I ſhall endeavour to advance a Notion in contradiction to the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Complaints of Covetouſneſs, That Charity is ſo far from impoveriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, that it tends to the bleſſing of God and the increaſe of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates. If this cou'd be but believ'd, it wou'd gratifie the Covetous and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:43329:46"/> Ambitious at once; and ſtop the Mouth of a conſiderable Objection (which I have not before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned) as well as ſettle an impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Truth: Which I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to do by Arguments drawn from Scripture, Reaſon, and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</p>
               <p>From Scripture I have this to ſay;<note place="margin">That prov'd by, <hi>firſt,</hi> Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</note> That what God hath promiſed muſt be performed, if our Ignorance or Infidelity doth not hinder it. But there is nothing plainer than a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of a full retribution (and that with advantage) of thoſe Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals we lay out upon the Account of Charity; and that not only in the next but in this Life. Thus <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon; The liberal Soul ſhall be made fat: and he that watereth, ſhall be watered himſelf,</hi> Prov. 11. 25. agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to what he affirms in other places: <hi>He that giveth to the Poor ſhall not lack,</hi> Prov. 28. 27. And, <hi>He that giveth to the poor, lendeth to the Lord; and that which he hath given, will he repay him again,</hi> Ch. 19. 17.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:43329:47"/> 
                  <hi>Foenerator Deo,</hi> (ſaith the Vulgar) he putteth his Money to uſe to the Lord; &amp; <hi>viciſſitudinem ſuam red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det ei,</hi> he will reſtore him his turn or ſhare. Thus <hi>David</hi> his Father; <hi>Bleſſed is he that conſidereth the poor and needy: the Lord will deliver him in the time of trouble. The Lord will preſerve him and keep him alive, and he ſhall be bleſſed upon the earth,</hi> Pſal. 41. 1, 2, &amp;c. St. <hi>Paul</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares Alms-deeds to Seed ſowen; and God's returns, to the Harveſt; and promiſes thereupon, that <hi>he that ſows bountifully ſhall reap bountifully, 2 Cor.</hi> 9. 6. The Original and Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar hath it, <hi>He that ſoweth in bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, ſhall reap of bleſſings,</hi> meaning temporal Bleſſings. And tho' ſome of theſe Promiſes may be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Life to come, (which yet makes the Encouragement the more conſiderable) yet others muſt be applied to this Life. But why ſhould we doubt this Truth, and what better Security can we have than our Saviour's Promiſe? <hi>Luke</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:43329:47"/> 6. 38. <hi>Give, and it ſhall be given you; good meaſure, ſhaken down, and running over, ſhall men give into your boſoms: for with the ſame meaſure you meet withal, it ſhall be meaſured to you again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From Reaſon. And if, after ſuch<note place="margin">2dly, <hi>By Reaſon.</hi>
                  </note> plain and pregnant Places of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, it were proper for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to conſult this more fallible Oracle, when the Matter is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by that which is infallible, we might receive further ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from Arguments drawn from God's Veracity, Juſtice, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; all which ſeem to be engag'd to make the charitable Man a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent as well as future Recompence: And that ſo much the more for En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement and Examples ſake. For, it is the moſt probable way to engage the Divine Benediction up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all we have. And altho' Men may be either forgetful or unjuſt, yet God cannot be untrue to his Word, when he hath promiſed that the Righteous ſhall be recompenced
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:43329:48"/> on Earth; or ſo unrighteous, as <hi>to neglect our work and labour of love, which we have ſhewed to his Name, in the miniſtring to the Saints,</hi> Heb. 6. 10.</p>
               <p>From Experience. <hi>David</hi> long<note place="margin">3dly, <hi>By Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
                  </note> ſince profeſſed, that in all the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his Life, he <hi>never ſaw the righteous forſaken, or his ſeed beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,</hi> Pſal. 37. 25. <hi>That the righteous is ever merciful, and lendeth; and thereupon his ſeed is bleſſed.</hi> And it is noted as an Aphoriſm by <hi>Solomon, That a good Man leaveth an Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to his Childrens Children.</hi> And even in theſe dark Times of Sin and Ignorance, I ſhall challenge Mankind to ſhew me one Inſtance, that ever prudent Charity made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Man poor; (and 'tis no longer Charity than 'tis Prudent and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious; nor can I think him Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent or Religious, that neglects his Family and fooliſhly gives all away, for I have and ever ſhall allow Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſervation the firſt ſhare.) In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:43329:48"/> other things may reduce the liberal Perſon to Poverty, as Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Suretiſhip, and other waſtful Crimes, that may poſſibly outweigh his Charity, and make Poverty ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for him; but for Charity alone, it muſt be followed with the Favours of Heaven, and the grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Acknowledgments and Retri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions of Earth. And this is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſilence the uſual Fears of Covetouſneſs, and beget in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral Breaſt a lively Hope of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, as well as future Recompences. For, who can deſire a more benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Bank than God's? Or, why may we not venture, when we have God's Promiſes, his Veracity, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and Goodneſs; yea, and our own Experience, that we ſhall have a fortunate Lot?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>§. XV.</head>
               <p>But you (<hi>Sir</hi>) and thoſe of your Character, with whom I preſume to deal in this Paper, are above Avarice, and its Fears and Jealouſies. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour moves you more, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:43329:49"/> let me uſe that as a Third Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to Charity: I mean,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The honourableneſs of<note place="margin">3. <hi>Charity a generous and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</hi>
                  </note> that Action. I know very well how much the World generally is miſtaken in the Notion of Honour; as tho' 'twas to be only found in Wars, Ruines, Murthers, Deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; in ſacking, burning, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Cities, and Countries; and, finally, in doing all the Miſchiefs one to another, that Revenge can invent, or Pride and Cruelty exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute. But theſe are falſe Notions, that make Men Tyrants inſtead of Hero's, and feared and hated inſtead of honoured. True Greatneſs of Mind conſiſts in diſpenſing Benefits to Mankind; in giving and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving; <hi>in looſing the Bonds of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and the heavy Burthens, and letting the oppreſſed go free; in dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling our Bread to the hungry, and bringing the Poor that are caſt out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Houſes; in covering the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and not hiding our ſelves from our own Fleſh.</hi> For then our <hi>Light
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:43329:49"/> ſhall break forth, as the morning out of the boſom of obſcurity, and our Darkneſs become as the Noon-day. Our Righteouſneſs ſhall go before us, and the Glory of the Lord ſhall be our Rere-ward.</hi> A generous Nature will rather enliven with genial Heat, than burn and deſtroy. God hath produced this beautiful World, and by his wonderful Providence hitherto hath preſerv'd it. 'Tis the Devil that wou'd firſt diſorder and then deſtroy it, and has therefore the Name of <hi>Abaddon</hi> and <hi>Apollyon.</hi> Charity comes from God, and all the Actions it produceth are Divine and God-like. 'Tis a great and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Grace, and what is common to us with the Deity. We cannot reach the Power of his Creation; but we may in ſome meaſure the Goodneſs of his Preſervation. An Action ſo full of Honour, and ſo deſerving it, that our bleſſed Lord, when he was to refine and ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate it in his Sermon from the Mount, gave us no new Rules a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:43329:50"/> it, but only a Caution not to be too proud of it. And tho' it wou'd injure the radical and ſelf-denying Graces to make Glory the chief End of Charity, yet I know not why I may not uſe it among others as an Encouragement to it, for it naturally follows it. <hi>For his Horn</hi> (to uſe the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Phraſe) <hi>ſhall be exalted with honour, and his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs endureth for ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>§. XVI. <hi>That Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded with Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as well as Earth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>4. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That I may mention no more: It is the part of every wiſe Man to conſult his future Good, and take care for a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being when he is turn'd out of this his preſent Stewardſhip. Our Lord from the wicked Policy of the unjuſt Steward in the Goſpel, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces a Leſſon both of Piety and Polity; <hi>And, I ſay unto you, make you friends of the Mammon of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, that when ye fail they may receive you into everlaſting habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</hi> Which I ſhall need but to render plain by this Paraphraſe:
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:43329:50"/> Whereas by the abuſe of Riches Men uſually render them Snares of the Devil, and Fewel to heat their Hell ſeven times hotter; learn ye from me the divine Chimiſtry, to extract Good out of Evil, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Advantages out of that which accidentally ruines ſo many. Uſe your Riches in Works of Piety and Charity; by which means you may make you Friends in the Court of Heaven, (as well as on Earth) that when ye fail and die, and ſo muſt leave this World, thoſe Friends that ye have made there, may cauſe you to be received into everlaſting Habitations. By theſe Friends I mean good Works; which, by the Mercies of God, and his gracious Acceptance, are crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an eternal Reward, far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their intrinſick value. And this is (I conceive) the true im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Words, and free from the affrightful Doctrines of Merit, whether of Condignity or Congrui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And we may in all Humility
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:43329:51"/> have reſpect to the recompence of the Reward. For our Lord to this purpoſe deſcribes the Circumſtances of the laſt Judgment, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. as tho' he wou'd encourage Men to Works of Charity when he tells us, That the Pious ſhould have their Heaven and the Kingdom pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them, from the beginning of the World, for or in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Works of Mercy, <hi>viz.</hi> For feeding, cloathing, and viſiting Chriſt's poor Members; and the Curſed their ſentence of Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for their neglecting of them. And if there be (as we are ſure there are) Degrees of Glory, and they may be increaſed every Day to the World's end, then judge to what an immenſe Summ the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Man's Stock of Glory may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to by the conſummation of all Things; while his Acts of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Charity every Year bring ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Souls to Heaven, whoſe good Deeds and Reward muſt in all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity redound to him that was the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:43329:51"/> occaſion of 'em. And ſuch muſt be the happy Condition of the Founders and Benefactors of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges, Halls, Hoſpitals, and other religious and charitable Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whoſe Reward ſhall not only continue, but be increaſed daily, in proportion to the Good it doth and ſhall do daily, till the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of all Things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>§. XVII. <hi>The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion; ſhewing the difference betwixt the Deſert and Reward of the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſals.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And here give me leave to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to you, the difference betwixt Self-ſerving on the one Hand, and Liberality and Charity on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and deſire you to conſider the different Methods of Diſtribution, and the different Deſerts and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; by which you may judge which is the more prudent way, of Diſpoſal in our lives-time, or Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement at our death. And for once let us ſuppoſe, That every rich Man has a Son to be Heir of his Eſtate and Fourtunes; yet even in that Caſe there is this to be ſaid.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:43329:52"/>
               <p>1. We think our ſelves happy<note place="margin">That of the Ordinary conſider'd.</note> when we can beget our like, and tranſmit our Nature to another, and ſo preſerve it from the common fate of Mortality. And yet, indeed, it is no more ours when we die than anothers; for then all Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ceaſe, and Kindred is at an end. And even while we live here (conſidering the conſtant Flux of Matter) there's very little of us in our Children, unleſs the Soul al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo cou'd be prov'd to be <hi>ex traduce.</hi> However, we call them ours, we give them an Original and Nature by Nutrition and Increaſe: But then we communicate to them our evil and corrupt Nature and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition, and (commonly) our Cuſtoms and Habits. If there be any Imperfection it is uſually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated, and we may view our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſelves in them: An Object of Grief more than Joy. And ſo much the more, when by the want of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, or a depraved one, when by Fondneſs and Lenity we make
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:43329:52"/> him twofold more the Child of Wrath than our ſelves. But if we cou'd be ſecure of his happy and proſperous Life, in reſpect of all his Capacities, yet this like wiſe muſt be taken into Conſideration, That Families as well as ſingle Men have their period; and two or three Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations uſually put an end to our Place and Name; and then where's the effect of all our Cares, Projects, Deſigns, Joys, and Griefs, when Strangers ſhall inherit our Labours? Well, but what's the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or future Reward for all our Cares and Troubles, in providing Eſtates for our Heirs, or Heirs for our Eſtates? Verily, nothing at all. We have here but our Labour for our Pains, and the thin aery Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of thinking we ſhall leave an Eſtate to our Children; or, rather, to we know not whom: Sometimes we have the mortification to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee that all ſhall be ſpent and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in a ſhort time; as 'tis ſaid of an eminent Perſon in a former
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:43329:53"/> Reign to have made this ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Bequeſt; <hi>Scelera omnia Edoardo Primogenito meo diſſipanda (neque unquam melius ſperavi) religo,</hi> &amp;c. And, if Souls departed have any Account of the Affairs of their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors here on Earth, it muſt be moſt commonly a very ſorrowful one; but, if they have none at all, it will not concern us who they are, and what they do. Thus for our preſent, and then for our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Reward, we can expect no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. For this is the Effect only of ſelf-love, to ſupport our ſelves firſt, and then our ſecond ſelves, our Heirs, and Aſſigns when we can hold it no longer; and ſo do the <hi>Heathens;</hi> and then what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward can we expect more than they? Or, rather, what Puniſhment may we not expect above them, who have a greater Light, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and Encouragements, and yet manage our earthly Talent moſtly worſe than they? And this is, in ſhort, the Account of our
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:43329:53"/> ordinary Diſpoſals of the Goods of Fortune, (as they are commonly called) and Deſerts and Rewards conſequent thereunto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>§. XVIII. <hi>That of the Charitable Perſons,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>2. Let us now, in the ſecond place, conſider thoſe of the Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perſon; and, for Inſtance ſake, that of the Founder of a College or School in particular. He cannot be ſuppos'd to be Childleſs, but has a numerous Family, and that ſelected out of the beſt Wits and Humours in the Nation, and the greateſt Perſons are glad to part with the moſt ingenious of their Sons to become his, and ſerve un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Rules. He preſcribes Laws, which they willingly bind them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by Oath to obſerve, with a greater Reverence and Care than the Commands of their natural Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; and they leave their Fathers and Mothers to become his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Their continual Practice is that of Vertue, Learning, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: And thus the worſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:43329:54"/> are rectified, and the beſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd, and all are mended, And when this Work is perfected, ſome go out into the World and are fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſerve God in his Church, the King, and their Country; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſucceed in their Places and Advantages: So that his Family is a Seminary of Religion and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and there is a ſucceſſion of it as long as the Sun and Moon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth. And when theſe have fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed their Courſes, and the end of all Things is come, he may preſent himſelf and them to his Maker, with the Words of the Prophet; <hi>Behold, Lord, I and the Children that thou haſt given me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>§. XIX.</head>
               <p>In Summ: Charity hath the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of any other Diſpoſal of Eſtate; and that in theſe Three Reſpects following: <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Charitable Perſon doth Good to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and not to his own Family only, (and I wou'd not be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, as if I pleaded for the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:43329:54"/> neglect of them) but the Good of others alſo; and therefore his Work is more Heroick, Diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, and remov'd from private Good, and ſo is more excellent. And he may ſay out of the Mouth of Wiſdom; <hi>Behold, I have not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccluſ. 24. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>for my ſelf only, but for all them that ſeek Wiſdom. Secondly,</hi> He doth the beſt Good, not only in ſupporting the Bodies, but dreſſing up the Souls, and cultivating of the Minds of Men for Religion and Vertue. And ſo the End of his Endeavours is the acquiſition of the greateſt preſent and future Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of Mind and Body here on Earth, and afterwards in Heaven. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Others Labours ceaſe and reſt, (as well as they from their Labours) but his continue, increaſe, and produce new Advantages dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and ſo will continue to do till the end of the World, unleſs the Supreme Providence ſuffers them to be invaded and diverted. And even in that Caſe the Pious Donor
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:43329:55"/> may reaſonably expect from the juſt God Rewards in proportion to the preſumptive Effects of his Work, and the Intention of the Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. So that let things happen how they will, he cannot miſs of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. If his Charity remains, his Reward increaſeth with its Fruits; but, if it be obſtructed by Fraud or Violence, yet it will be remune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated according to the uprightneſs of his Intention.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>§. XX.</head>
               <p>In a word: Every Action of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we do here is recorded above, and hath its Reward apportion'd there, even to Intereſt upon Intereſt, and all the poſſible Degrees of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement; which the Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience can eaſily foreſee, and will adjuſt according to the Meaſures of his Mercies. And this Reward is as far above the inherent Worth of the Work as Heaven is above the Earth, or the Regions of Bliſs above this Vale of Tears. Whatſoever we do for our ſelves, or our Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:43329:55"/> we leave behind us, as Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties we owe to Nature, for which ſhe pays us here. But what we do for God, and his Servants for his ſake, follow us into the ſtate of the dead, and into the Tribunal of our Judge, and plead for us; where they cannot but have a benign Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, from him <hi>who is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Fatherleſs, and who pleads the Cauſe of Orphans and Widows; even God in his Holy Habitation.</hi> And with this I will conclude the ſecond Head of this Diſcourſe, and prepare to ſpeak of the Third in that which follows.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:43329:56"/>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:43329:56"/>
            <head>AN ESSAY TO Revive the Neceſſity OF <hi>Ancient Piety.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§. I. <hi>Why the Author treats of Works of Piety in the laſt place.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Subject of this Second Addreſs, is the Third End for which it pleaſes the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Bounty to entruſt us with an Earthly Portion; and that is the Promotion of the Honour of God, and the making his Perfections, and particularly his Goodneſs known
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:43329:57"/> to Mankind, that they may with us be induc'd to render him the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour due to his Name, and the Tribute of Praiſe and Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. And this by the order of Nature and Reaſon ought to have claimed the firſt Place in theſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes; as his Dues were to be firſt offered up, and ſeparated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his own People, before they were to make uſe of the remainder. Beſides, this is the End of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of our own Part, and the End of our Diſtribution to others; of Self-preſervation and Charity, both ought to aim at his Glory, and therefore it ought firſt to be trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of. But in this ungrateful Age, in which we take (like the Beaſt of the Field) what is beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, without ever looking up to Heaven and acknowledging the Hand that diſtributes it; in this prophane Age, in which our Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Profits are only conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and God's Honour not at all, or not often; in this bigotted,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:43329:57"/> and yet irreligious Age, in which 'tis thought Superſtition and <hi>Prieſt-Craft,</hi> to plead for any thing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the continuance of God's Service, (becauſe they are to be his Receivers) wherein ſuch Doctrines as theſe are quite out-dated, and ſtrange to our Ears, and Men think their Eſtates not concern'd at all to maintain the Worſhip of God: In an Age wherein 'tis thought that Church-men have too much ſtill, and a covetous Eye is caſt upon the <hi>large Revenues of Biſhops, Deans and Chapters;</hi> wherein all chargea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Worſhip is thought needleſs, and ſo many inſpir'd Ignorants ſet up for Miniſters, and tender a cheap Worſhip, or ſuch as will coſt nothing: I ſay, in ſuch an Age as this is, I muſt be content that God's Cauſe ſhou'd come on laſt, and that he have the leaſt ſhare in our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates rather than none at all. And yet tho' it comes laſt, yet it ſhall not be leaſt treated of, but be the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the following Papers; in
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:43329:58"/> which I ſhall endeavour to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this Aſſertion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. II. <hi>That every Man is bound, to the utmoſt of his Power, to promote the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Maſter, and maintain his Service, and (for the ſake of that, and to that purpoſe) thoſe that are to officiate in the ſame, and that with his Eſtate and Fortunes. And, that he that is able to do it (which is the Caſe of moſt Men more or leſs) and doth it not, miſ-imploys his Talent, anſwers not the End for which it was committed to his Charge, and muſt give an Account of that Neglect at the last Day.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>That this Truth may appear, I muſt firſt define what I mean by the Object of our Piety, the Glory of God, and then diſtinguiſh concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Ways of promoting of it.</p>
               <p>The Glory and Honour of God,<note place="margin">What is meant by the Glory of God, or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</note> or Divine Worſhip, is the humble and reverential Agnition of his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and of all his Glorious Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes;
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:43329:58"/> his Supremacy, Power, Goodneſs, and other infinite Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: And the Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that we are his Creatures, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon him for Life and Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and receive all the good things neceſſary thereunto at his Bounty; which is the ſubject-matter of our Prayers and Praiſes.</p>
               <p>The act of exhibiting thoſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments,<note place="margin">How this is exhibited.</note> is either mediate, or immediate.</p>
               <p>We glorifie God mediately,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately: By mediate, as that tends to his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi>
                  </note> when we do any thing that natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally tends to theſe Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Thus the doing of every good Work is for his Glory, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it may and doth naturally tend to ſet it forth. Thus all the Works of Nature and Art, the Knowledge of the great Syſtem of the World, and Natural Philoſophy teach his Praiſes. Thus all Moral<note place="margin">As Moral and Matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy.</note> Works of Vertue (as Equity, or Juſtice, Comity, Urbanity, Liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Fortitude, Temperance, and ſuch like) tend to his Glory in their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:43329:59"/> for the Good of Mankind, and in the Subject where they are found, becauſe of his planting there. Even Polity (the well-inſtitution of Kingdoms, and Reciprocal Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Governors and Subjects) leads us to the Providential Care of God for our Good, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his Praiſes. In a word, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth naturally incline us to think upon God, and reflect upon his Power or Goodneſs, is a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Act of glorifying him. And thus the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> having conſidered the ſeveral Acts of Providence o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſeveral ſorts of Men in the varieties of their Lives, reflects ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry naturally upon his Goodneſs, and thence takes occaſion to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort Men to praiſe him; <hi>O that men</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 107.</note> 
                  <hi>wou'd therefore praiſe the Lord for his Goodneſs, and for his wonderful Works to the Children of Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, as natural and moral Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy tend in their conſequences and mediately to the Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice which we owe our Maker,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:43329:59"/> ſo do all Foundations, Societies, and<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Schools of Learning, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities, how they tend to the advancing Divine Service,</hi> &amp;c.</note> Seminaries of Learning and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, deſign'd for the ſame uſes. And here I cannot but remember, and at the ſame time celebrate thoſe Nurſeries of every thing that is Good and Commendable, <hi>The two flouriſhing <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities of our Land,</hi> and that with all Thankfulneſs to God, and Acknowledgments of the Munificence of the Founders and Benefactors of each Society, that compoſe thoſe Auguſt and Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Bodies: That God was pleaſed to incline the Hearts of thoſe good Men to employ their Riches to ſuch Advantages of Religion, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſuch Foundations to the Good of Mankind, amongſt the Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſo many pretended Houſes of Religion in theſe three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. Places founded at firſt, without all queſtion, with ſincere Intentions of extraordinary Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Devotion, but degenerated in latter Times into Idleneſs, Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, and all manner of Senſuality,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:43329:60"/> and ſo from Houſes of Prayer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Dens of Thieves. In the deſolution of theſe, thoſe remained untouched, (nay, augmented and eſtabliſhed) becauſe free from their Crimes; and may they continue and flouriſh whilſt this Machine of Heaven and Earth continues, and not determine but in its Deſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>How naturally, and how much theſe tend to the Service of God, is obvious to every one that conſiders, That the End of their Erection, and the daily exerciſe of their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, is, <hi>Firſt,</hi> To ſmooth over the Aſperities, mend the Deformities, and finiſh the Imperfections of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature; to introduce Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Urbanity, Bowels of Mercies, humbleneſs of Mind, Meekneſs, Long-ſuffering, Forbearance, and Forgiveneſs, and, indeed, an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Charity. Theſe Graces are requir'd in Chriſtians by the great Apoſtle of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc'd by the Univerſity-Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:43329:60"/> which ſoftens our harſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and melts them down into a Temper to receive ſuch Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And, beſides, by the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual practice of Vertue, and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Converſation, and by the Admonitions and Examples of their Superiors, the Inclinations to our native Vices are weakned and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and contrary Diſpoſitions and Habits ſuper-induc'd, neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry all the remaining parts of our lives to our Politick, as well as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, Capacities. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Their Exerciſe is the Improvement of their rational Faculties, whereby we differ from the Beaſts, and this helps them not only for Diſcourſe and Converſation, but for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of Truth and Falſhood when it is dreſt up in its ſhape and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Natural Philoſophy and the inquiſition into the ſtate of Nature, the Syſtem of the World, and the Works of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are taught to ſee things with other Eyes than the Vulgar,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:43329:61"/> and diſcover the Greatneſs and Goodneſs of our Creator, and fear and honour him accordingly. <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> The heavenly Doctrine of the Knowledge of our ſelves, <hi>Autarchy,</hi> or the Government of Luſts, Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, and Paſſions: To live as ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Creatures, that are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebriated with preſent Enjoyments, but foreſee and provide for Futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and another Life. Theſe are all excellent Preparations and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to the higheſt of all Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies, (which is likewiſe taught and practiſed within thoſe Walls) the Knowledge of God, and our Duty thereupon, according to both natural and revealed Religion. And therefore from theſe Nurſeries, thoſe that are fit are tranſplanted into the Church (as well as State) <hi>as workmen that need not be aſhamed, rightly dividing the Word of Truth, throughly furniſhed with all good Works,</hi> and fitted to exhibit the Wants of their ſeveral Flocks to God, as well as their own, by thoſe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:43329:61"/> Proſtrations of Mind and Body in the immediate Acts of his Worſhip, commonly call'd <hi>Divine Service,</hi> which I am next to ſpeak of.</p>
               <p>For there is a more immediate<note place="margin">2dly, <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately.</hi>
                  </note> act of exhibiting this Worſhip; and that is, the actual homage of the agnition the agnition of God, and his Attributes, and our dependance on him: And this is done only in Prayers and Praiſes. And in this ſtrict Sence, neither reading, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, preaching the Word, nor fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting of Sermons, is Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, or the immediate act of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. And tho' they have an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Aſpect that way, and tend to it, yet they are not the thing it ſelf: Wherein (by the way) we may note the great miſtake of the Zealots of this Age, who place Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in nothing but Sermonizing and Hearing, and ſlight all the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and holy Methods of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching the Deity. And, inſtead of theſe, gratifie their itching Ears with long canting Harangues, and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:43329:62"/> the Froth of Fancy, which they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire becauſe they know not what to make of it. Whereas Religion conſiſts in the Application of the Mind to the Deity, with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Submiſſion and grateful Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments: And theſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from a pure and ſanctified Mind in Thoughts or Words proper, ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and throughly examin'd, that we may offer unto God a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Service, or the Service becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reaſonable Creatures. This is the true and eſſential Worſhip of God, the higheſt Duty Man is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, and the End of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: 'Tis our great Duty upon Earth, and the Imployment of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which ſhall continue to all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. There the four (ſtrange, but) glorious living Creatures, and the four and twenty Elders, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all the heavenly Hoſt, reſt not Night nor Day, but joyn al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together in perpetual Hymns of Praiſes and Thankſgivings, caſting down their Crowns before the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:43329:62"/> Throne, and ſaying, <hi>Thou art wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, O Lord, to receive Glory, and Honour, and Power; for thou haſt created all things, and for thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure they are and were created.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§. III. <hi>That Works of Piety, or the Service of God, ought to be promoted by our Eſtates, proved by Five Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This is that which we are bound to do our ſelves in the ſeveral Pauſes and Intervals we enjoy from the noiſe of this World: And this we are bound to promote to the utmoſt of our Power, and with our Lives and Fortunes. And that you may know how your Eſtate may be ſerviceable, and is liable to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to this immortal Work, (the continuance of Divine Service) I ſhall make a gradual Advance in theſe Five Propoſitions follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 1. God is to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped<note place="margin">Prop. 1. <hi>That God is to be worſhipped, and his Service promoted.</hi>
                  </note> by Mankind. And here, to diſtinguiſh a little further (which falls properly in the aforegoing <hi>Section,</hi> but was forgot there) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the mediate Acts of Divine
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:43329:63"/> Worſhip. They are either inward<note place="margin">Of inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward acts of Worſhip, and that both are required.</note> or outward. The inward is the act of the Mind, and conſiſts in hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and grateful Acknowledgments of his infinite Goodneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The outward act is the external Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this inward Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And this Expreſſion is made by ſenſible Signs; ſuch are, <hi>Firſt,</hi> The articulate Words of Prayers and Praiſes. And then, <hi>Secondly,</hi> The inarticulate Signs made by the Genuflexions and Proſtrations of the Body. By theſe outward acts we make our Bodies Parties in the Worſhip, and give ſenſible Indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to others what we are doing, thereby inſtructing and encouraging them to do the like: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is proper for the publick Service of God; becauſe 'tis the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viſible and ſenſible act of which our Fellow-Creatures, Men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels can take cognizance. And from theſe outward Signs of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Humility have the <hi>Greeks</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken occaſion to call Divine Service,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:43329:63"/> or Adoration, in their Language, προσκύνησις, a bowing down, or Proſtration of the Body; according to the devout <hi>Pſalmiſt; O, come let us worſhip, and bow down, and kneel before the Lord our Maker.</hi> I will not make compariſon betwixt theſe two acts, the inward and the outward, (each have their ſeveral uſe and excellency) becauſe they muſt not be ſeparated, eſpecially in publick Prayer. For, as the Body and Soul make the Man, ſo the external and internal Service of God do make Divine Service.</p>
               <p>To come to the Propoſition then.<note place="margin">The Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition prov'd from the Obligations we have to Truth, Gratitude, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnity.</note> 'Tis abſolutely neceſſary that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man ſhou'd worſhip his Maker, with the inward and (if he be not incapacitated) with outward Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. And this will appear from the Obligations we have to, <hi>firſt,</hi> Truth; <hi>ſecondly,</hi> Gratitude; <hi>third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> Indempnity or Pardon of Sin.</p>
               <p>1. We are bound to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge every Truth. But, that God is an infinite Being in himſelf, and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:43329:64"/> infinitely Good to us, is a great and eternal Truth, and therefore ought to be recogniz'd and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, elſe we are injurious to Truth it ſelf. 2. We are bound to Gratitude, and that obliges us to acknowledge God's Bounty. And, as Tenants ſwear Fealty, and do their Homage, (as an acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord's original Right upon theſe Terms deriv'd to them) ſo Gratitude obliges us to a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of God's Right over all things, and his gracious Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of what is uſeful to us. But then we have a Third Obligation; which is, the want we have of Indempni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For we muſt be ſenſible of the depravation of our Nature, and our neglect of Duty; and, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that we are obnoxious to the Divine Juſtice, if it be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton'd and reconcil'd to us: And the way to obtain that, is by hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Confeſſions and Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to which God in his Holy Word hath annext a full Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 1. 9.</note>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:43329:64"/> and hath pawn'd his Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Juſtice for the ſame: And this is a Third Obligation to Divine Worſhip.</p>
               <p>Behold (<hi>Sir</hi>) the triple Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Religion, and eſpecially of Divine Worſhip. And here I cannot but tremble to make the Application to thoſe many (to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all) in theſe luke-warm Times. To thoſe (I mean) that are become ſo indifferent as to God's Service, that they preferr the meaneſt of their Pleaſures, as well as the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of their Profits, to it. That ſerve God when they have nothing elſe to do, and go to their Prayers when they have neither Friends nor occaſions to interrupt them. That lay aſide their Duty to God to go to a Feaſt, or Meeting, and leave the Chappel for a Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>match. Theſe (and who are not ſuch in this degenerate Age?) do in effect, and for that turn at leaſt, deny God, and ſin againſt Truth, Gratitude, and the Pardon they
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:43329:65"/> ſtand in need of. They uſe that daily Bread which they are not at leiſure to ask at God's Hand, and take his Liberality, and cannot ſtay to thank him, but put him off till ſome other time. They diſown their Creator and Benefactor for that time, and will make him ſtay till they can a while to make their Acknowledgments. And how great a Crime this is, do but judge (<hi>Sir</hi>) by the like in any of your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, whom for leſs than this you wou'd diſcard for ever. I cannot ſtay to proſecute this ſeaſonable Reflection, (you may improve it by running up the Parallel as far as it will go, and making Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to your own Conſcience) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I muſt paſs on to the next Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; which is this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. IV. Prop. 2. <hi>That God is daily to be worſhipped. Of publick and private Worſhip.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 2. This Divine Service muſt be perform'd publickly or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, ſolemnly or occaſionally e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Day. The publick and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn way of ſerving God is as far
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:43329:65"/> beyond that which is private, as the Light of the Sun is beyond that of a Candle, and muſt be ſo much the more acceptable, as your Servants ready performance of your publick Command wou'd be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his denying of it before all the Company, and then perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it in ſecret. Not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs God (when we are enjoyn'd) is to deny him: And our Saviour has declar'd, That <hi>he that denies him before Men, ſhall be denied by him before his Father and the Holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi> For this and other Reaſons, I ſay, 'tis our Duty to worſhip God publickly and ſolemnly. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Mens Circumſtances may va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, publick Prayers cannot be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways had, and there may be emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies which may prevent them, and ſometimes the neceſſaries to Self-preſervation hinders them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in the meaner ſort, (who literally undergo the conſequent of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin; <hi>In the ſweat of thy brows ſhalt thou eat thy bread.</hi>) I
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:43329:66"/> add therefore, in defect of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip, that which is private or occaſional; For, where the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick is intermitted, the private muſt ſupply that neglect; and, where the ſettled Hour of Prayer cannot be attended, the occaſional muſt atone for the omiſſion. The firſt, and (in defect of that) the ſecond muſt be our daily Exerciſe. And he that cannot wait upon God in his Temple, muſt yet meet him in his Cloſet; and if even that cannot be (which is ſeldom known) he muſt yet ſend ſome ſhort Eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation up wards, as Envoys to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe his neceſſary Neglect.</p>
               <p>But however this is done (for<note place="margin">That one of theſe is to be offered up daily.</note> God is ready to allow us what we can reaſonably demand) it ought to be done daily. Life is call'd our Day, and each Day is a new Life. Night is a true Image of the Days of Darkneſs, which are many, and Sleep of Death. We ceaſe to be our own, and have no ſigns of Life but Reſpiration; which is only a
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:43329:66"/> Pledge that we ſhall wake again; we know no Body, and are dead to the World, and all its Concerns. The Morning of the Day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is our daily Reſurrection, when we receive a new Life, and riſe up from our Grave-Clothes, and dreſs us again for the Buſineſſes of the Day. Seeing then we receive eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Day a new Life, and begin a new Work, can it be thought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable that we ſhould be bound to deſire a Bleſſing on the ſame? Or, that being a wakned from the Regions of Darkneſs and Shadow of Death, we ſhou'd make our Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments for that new Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? We ſalute our Friends every Morning, as reſtor'd to the <hi>de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo,</hi> but ſhall we paſs by God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaluted? Beſides, 'tis the dictate of Nature to begin the Day with God, a procuration of his Aſſiſtance, and a Bleſſing upon our Undertakings. The <hi>Perſians</hi> us'd to adore the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Sun, the Image and Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation (as they thought) of the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:43329:67"/> Supreme Deity. And the <hi>Jews</hi> had their Morning and Evening times of Sacrifice and ſolemn Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: And the Apoſtles thought it their duty to frequent them, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 46. &amp; <hi>c.</hi> 3. 1. The religious and devout Chriſtians of the Primitive Times had ſeveral ſettled Hours of Prayer every day. It wou'd be thought too much Superſtition to imitate, or ſtrictneſs to enjoyn the like to this Licentious Age: Yet our bleſſed Lord (below whoſe Commands we cannot go) hath ordered us all to ask <hi>day by day our daily Bread.</hi> And ſuppoſe God ſhou'd ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to our ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, (I mean) ſhou'd not give us what we are not at leiſure to ask; ſuppoſe he ſhou'd put us out of his Protection for but one day, what would follow? Why, no leſs than a ſeizure of the evil Angels upon Body and Soul, while ungarded. Or, if he ſhou'd withdraw his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting Hand, what wou'd be the Effect? Why, nothing leſs than
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:43329:67"/> death and the deſolution of the Man. Beſides, 'tis an omiſſion that can proceed from nothing but a diſingenious and baſe Ingratitude, unworthy of a rational Being, or of the Nature of Man: And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech God to lay it home to all our Hearts for an univerſal Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>§. V. Prop. 3. <hi>That there is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity for a ſettled Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the ſame.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 3. To aſſiſt us in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Addreſſes, as well as to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite us to them, there is a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that there ſhould be a ſort of Men ſelected from others, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe we call uſually the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, the more proper Inſtruments of Divine Worſhip. And the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of theſe appears from hence: Man is generally immers'd in Cares and the Affairs of this World; and the Buſineſs of this Life is apt to take up all his Thoughts, and bank his Reſolutions of Duty. Beſides, he is blinded by Self-love, and apt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:43329:68"/> to flatter himſelf, ſo that he cannot make a true judgment of his Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Eſtate; and wants upon both Accounts a daily Monitor, as to the things of God. Add to this, he is carried headlong with the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Paſſions beyond all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and loves and hates with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meaſure. His Appetites cheat and delude him, and the Devil is ready to improve them to evil Acts; and the Admonitions of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience cannot be harkned to. And all theſe unite to make him not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable at all times to exhibit a due and ſeaſonable worſhip to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker: And therefore God by the Law of Nature, as well as by his revealed Will, hath taught Men to have ſtanding Miniſters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who at once ſhould be Moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Aſſiſtants in our religious Applications, who ſhou'd at the ſame time call upon us to pray, and pray with us and for us; who ſhou'd <hi>exhort and rebuke with all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> and keep us (as far as thoſe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:43329:68"/> means can prevail with us) in our way to Heaven. Hence it is that in all Nations, where there was any Notion of a God and Religion, (and that was every where) there was alſo a ſeparate ſort of Men call'd <hi>Prieſts,</hi> to aſſiſt them as to the things of God and their well-in tended (tho' miſtaken) Devotions. Thus it has been from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſo it continues to this day, even amongſt the <hi>Heathens, Pagans,</hi> and <hi>Indians,</hi> who have no other Law but that of Nature to guide them. So it was amongſt the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs</hi> before the giving of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law, where the chief of each Family did this Office, as having in all probability the moſt Wiſdom as well as the moſt Authority. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Oeconomy in that Nation, this Office was annext to one Tribe, (but this was but a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional and Temporal Conſtitution) and under that of the Chriſtian; theſe are uſually called <hi>the Clergy.</hi> A ſort of Men begun by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:43329:69"/> (the chief Corner-Stone) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued from him to the Apoſtles, and from them to others down to us: Theſe receive a derivative Power to intercede for their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Flocks, inſtruct and build them up in the moſt Holy Faith, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter to them the Pledges of Grace and Salvation. Theſe things cannot be denied as to matters of Fact, or the reaſon of the Thing; and he that ſhall have the forehead to do it, will at the ſame time im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach the Wiſdom of God in the Holy Scriptures, as well as in the Law of Nature, and is no better than a proud conceited Atheiſt or Enthuſiaſt: And ſo I leave him to proceed to the Fourth Propoſition, which follows.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>§. VI. Prop 4. <hi>That the Miniſtry ought to have a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent and ſufficient Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 4. This ſort of Men thus ſet apart for the Purpoſes of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the Service of God, are to be maintain'd with a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency ſufficient for that Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:43329:69"/>
               <p>And here I deſire not to be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, for I dream not of Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and worldly Pomp. And what an envious ſort of People a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us have to object, ſhall be taken into Conſideration in its due place. I ſhall only plead for a Competency that may enable them to attend upon their Office with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtraction or worldly Avoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: And if that were allowed it were ſufficient, and under ſuch a Sufficiency it cannot he performed. The only Queſtion will be, what ought to be accounted ſuch a Suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency. And here let me not be thought impertinent if I enquire into two Things. <hi>Firſt,</hi> What the Supreme Wiſdom did heretofore think ſo, and ſhew how plentifully they were then provided for, both under <hi>Judaiſm</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> how the Church came to be impoveriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and what were the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of the ſame. <hi>Secondly,</hi> What by Parity of Reaſon may be thought ſuch a Sufficiency now.</p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:43329:70"/>
               <p>1. If we enquire of former Times<note place="margin">What God himſelf heretofore aſſign'd for a Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency. What a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Patriarchs.</note> and the Days that are now long paſt, we ſhall eaſily perceive what the Wiſdom of God thought ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the Support of ſo holy and abſtracted an Office. From the beginning of the World till the giving of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law from Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> which was above 2400 Years, the Prieſthood was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted by the Head of each Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the Princes were alſo Prieſts, the Sacred and Secular Powers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing united. But after God had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail'd the Prieſthood on the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Aaron</hi> (inſtead of the Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born,<note place="margin">Exod. 13.</note> which were always accounted his) he choſe the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> (of which <hi>Aaron</hi> was a Branch) to<note place="margin">Numb. 3.</note> attend the Prieſts and the Service of the Tabernacle. So that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of that Nation was divided into Prieſts and <hi>Levites:</hi> Thoſe the Principals, theſe the Aſſiſtants: Thoſe to perform the moſt ſolemn Acts of Worſhip, theſe to attend them, and to perform the inferior;
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:43329:70"/> and they were anſwerable to our Prieſts and Deacons. And amongſt the Prieſts there were then (as there be now) ſeveral Degrees (as the High-Prieſts, the Chief of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral<note place="margin">
                     <hi>What a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the</hi> Jews; <hi>and God's large Proviſion for them.</hi>
                  </note> Courſes and ordinary Prieſts) each dignified and diſtinguiſhed, and endow'd with Eſtates equal to their ſeveral Stations. The loweſt of that Miniſtry were the <hi>Levites.</hi> And, as to them, if we conſider their Number, they were not the fortieth part of the whole Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and yet it is obſerved by learned Men (that have computed it) that their Portion (what by Cities, and the Glebe round about to One thouſand Cubits every way, according to the Cubit of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, which was as big again as the ordinary Cubit, and what by the Tythes of all <hi>Iſrael</hi>) was four times as much as that of any other the greater Tribes. So liberal was God in thoſe Days to the Inferior Clergy, that tho' their Number was far ſmaller, yet their Portion
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:43329:71"/> was far greater than the reſt of the Peoples, and they loſt nothing, but got much by having God to be their <hi>Pay-Maſter,</hi> who allowed them E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates <hi>ſeven or eight</hi> times as much as he did to thoſe of other Tribes. Then for the Prieſts (of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Family of <hi>Aaron</hi>) they had the Firſt-Fruits of all things the Earth produced; as Corn, Wine, and Oil, (and he was a Man of an evil Eye, that offered under the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth part:) They had alſo the Firſt-Fruits of Cattle, clean and unclean; the firſt in kind, the other to be redeemed at a Price. They had the Firſt-born of Man to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed at <hi>five Shekels</hi> a piece, being likewiſe the <hi>Shekel</hi> of the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: They had all the Vows, Gifts, and Offerings, and all Males were to appear before God thrice every Year, and none to appear empty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handed. And beſides all this, they had thirteen Cities with their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs of the ſame Dimenſions with the former. So that every Prieſt,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:43329:71"/> conſidering the ſmalneſs of their Number, could not chuſe but live (if he wou'd himſelf) in a plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Condition, far above Want, and nearer to that of great Men than the common People. What Proviſion was made for the Chief of every Courſe, I remember not, but the <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> had the Tenth of the <hi>Levites Portion,</hi> and a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue equal to many (ſome ſay <hi>three</hi> or <hi>four thouſand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) Levites,</hi> ſuitable to that of the Princes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom he was accounted the chiefeſt. Now let any Man tell me why God ſhou'd thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for thoſe that perform'd his Worſhip, after ſuch an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry manner, above others under the Law; was it not to free 'em from Wants, and conſequently from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt? And if ſo, (as none can deny) if we have a Specimen of the Divine Allotment in thoſe Days of the largeſt Meaſures, why ſhould we think that he is not of the ſame Mind now? Or, that he would
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:43329:72"/> have his Prieſts under the Goſpel live upon <hi>Alms</hi> as <hi>Beggars?</hi> Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeeing there is the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the thing it ſelf, and he hath declared nothing to the contrary. But this will be better clear'd by taking a view of that Competen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which his Providence order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Miniſters under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>§. VII. <hi>The large Proviſion God made for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, in the Primitive Times.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Tho' our Lord choſe Poverty as a ſtate of Life beſt ſuiting his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of redeeming Mankind; and his Apoſtles were of mean Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, and forc'd to leave what they had, as unportable Matter, which they cou'd not (nor indeed needed) carry with them about the World, whither they were ſent to publiſh the Goſpel; yet, no ſooner was the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> given, and thoſe their <hi>mighty Powers</hi> confirm'd to them, (the leaſt of which was of more worth than a Crown and Scepter) but we find that they commanded all that their Converts
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:43329:72"/> had. And, in recompence of their own Loſſes, receiv'd their Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes whole Eſtates in Money at their Feet and Diſpoſal. The right of Tythes and Offerings (which was appropriated during the <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Law</hi> to that Tribe and Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood) reverted now to its old Channel: And that Prieſthood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at an end, they return'd to God's Miniſters of what Nation or Family ſoever they were. This our Lord himſelf intimated in the Sentence of giving <hi>to</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſar'<hi>s, and unto God the things that are God's;</hi> by which laſt the Primitive Fathers (who muſt beſt know his Mind) ſay he meant the reſtoration of God's due (his <hi>Tythes and Offerings</hi>) to his Servants they now properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd to; and thereby laying down a Maxim or Foundation for the right of the <hi>Chriſtian Prieſthood.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> alludes to this, or ſome other Ordination of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, when he maintains the Prieſts
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:43329:73"/> Right under the Goſpel to the Dues of the Altar upon our Lord's Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Even ſo (as the Miniſters of the Temple and the Altar were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Things of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Altar, which were Tythes and Offerings) <hi>hath the Lord or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that they that preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel,</hi> 1 Cor. 9. 14. But thoſe Times wou'd not bear that Truth, and therefore it was not ſeaſonable to declare it in plain Terms, or preſs it upon the Churches; leſt the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould be ſcandaliz'd at it, and cry out Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege, and the Devil ſhould have an Objection of pretended Covetouſneſs and Self-Intereſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Propagators</hi> of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. It was therefore abundantly ſufficient to aſſert the Miniſters Rights in general Words, and in ſuch Terms that they knew the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Chriſtians would interpret to the Churches Settlement. Beſides, Tythes cou'd neither be demanded without Offence, nor paid, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:43329:73"/> in thoſe Times; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Providence ordered Things ſo that they needed them not: For the Believers with themſelves made the Apoſtles a Preſent of all that they had; and left them to be Stewards and Diſtributers of it, as they ſhou'd think fit. Offerings ſupply'd the Place of Tythes, which were ſo conſiderable during thoſe Times of Trouble and Perſecution, that not only the ſucceeding <hi>Biſhops, Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> but the <hi>Poor</hi> alſo were plentifully main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, and that in all Places whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtianity extended it ſelf: And this till the Times of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> who ſettled Peace and its Rights to the Church, and Tythes amongſt the reſt; which cou'd not be regularly and univerſally paid before; tho' they might and were privately and in ſome Places, (where ſuffered) and therefore we read of ſome Churches endow'd before. But be that as it will: After the time of this <hi>Chriſtian Emperor,</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:43329:74"/> Churches were built and endow'd by <hi>Pious Men,</hi> who gave to them Portions of <hi>Glebe,</hi> and the <hi>Biſhop of the Dioceſs</hi> allotted and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated Portions of Tythes to the new-built Churches, ſuch as was ſufficient to maintain the <hi>Miniſter of Religion</hi> plentifully, and enable him to be hoſpitable, and to give to the Poor. This was the <hi>Original of Parochial Rights;</hi> and by theſe means, theſe Portions of Tythes, by little and little, were derived from the Biſhop (who was at firſt the <hi>Grand Proprietor</hi> and <hi>Receiver</hi> of them in his Dioceſs) to the <hi>Pariſh-Prieſt;</hi> to whom likewiſe, with the Profits, he derived alſo part of his Charge and Care (the <hi>Curam animarum</hi>) of thoſe in ſuch and ſuch Precincts: And this laſt is done to every new <hi>Incumbent</hi> to this Day, and it is call'd the <hi>Biſhops Inſtitution</hi> to the <hi>Benefice.</hi> The reſt of the Tythes, Offerings, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, were reſerv'd to the <hi>Cathedral Church of the Biſhops Sea,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:43329:74"/> and the Prieſts</hi> there reſident, who lived longer together in common, till Abuſes made it neceſſary to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate likewiſe their Allowances, which we call at this Day <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends.</hi> This was the Work of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral hundred Years more or leſs, and ſooner or later in the Nations wherein Chriſtianity was ſettled; during which time God ſtirred up the Hearts of Pious Men, both Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical and others, to endow and ſettle the Revenues of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Churches, that the <hi>Paſtors</hi> or (as they are now call'd) <hi>Rectors</hi> of them liv'd above Contempt, kept Hoſpitality, maintain'd the Poor, (for then there needed no Laws for their Suſtenance by Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, as now) and ſo waited comfortably on their Office. Their Gifts were great, and Offerings many. No Man came to the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Altar</hi> empty-handed, and none died but he gave ſomething in his Will to his Pariſh-Church, (if not to that of the Dioceſs) beſides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:43329:75"/> 
                  <hi>Legacies and Mortuaries.</hi> Their Conveyances were made to God and ſuch a Church, and that by the ſureſt ways, and under the ſevereſt Curſes in caſe of Alienati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons imaginable; by which they thought to enſure and perpetuate their ſeveral Pieties beyond the Power of <hi>Sacrilegious Alienations.</hi> They gave to God, becauſe they thought no Man durſt rob him, not remembring that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were<note place="margin">Mal. 3. 6.</note> long ago charg'd with that Crime. They hedg'd about their Donati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with <hi>Denunciations of Hell and Damnation</hi> to thoſe that ſhou'd be ſo bold as to pervert them to other Uſes. But all in vain. There is nothing durable in this World. The <hi>wild Boar out of the Wood firſt threw down the Hedges, and ſo the little Foxes of the Hills were let in to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the Grapes.</hi> An Atheiſtical Covetouſneſs is able to overthrow all Fences, and when the Fear of God is departed from a Place, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can ſecure the Gifts of Piety
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:43329:75"/> or Property but humane Laws, and they too, were drawn into the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy.</hi> And yet even this cou'd not be done quickly and directly, nor had Iniquity the forehead to invade God's Poſſeſſions, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the diſguiſe of Zeal and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; which was thus effected.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>§. VIII. <hi>How the Revenues of the Church came to be alienated.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>There hath been in the Church very anciently ſome ſevere melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Chriſtians, who ſeparated themſelves from the World, and its Temptations, and Follies, to ſerve God in Solitude and Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; and ſome in Times of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution were forc'd to it, ſuch were the <hi>Eremits</hi> and <hi>Anchorites:</hi> Theſe afterward were reduc'd to Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Societies under ſeveral Rules, and Orders; and were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Friars.</hi> Theſe in time engroſs'd to themſelves all the Credit of Chriſtianity, and were call'd (by way of Eminency) the <hi>Religious.</hi> Their Rules were ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, their Diet very poor, their
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:43329:76"/> Hours of Devotion long, often and exact; their Diſcipline moſt morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, and their Holineſs ſo great, that their very Habit in thoſe Times of Superſtition was thought effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to ſave the Sinner that was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in it. By this means the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Secular Clergy</hi> (as they were call'd for diſtinction ſake) were ſlighted, and the Paſtors of Pariſhes that had care of Souls were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpected; and a ſeverer Religion than Chriſt ordain'd was preſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Men as neceſſary. And hence the Patrons of Livings, (which uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally were the firſt Endowers of the Churches and their Heirs) the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Dioceſſes, and Popes of</hi> Rome ran altogether upon building of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries</hi> and <hi>Religious Houſes,</hi> and endowing of them; and to this purpoſe fell to appropriating the Tythes of moſt of the conſiderable Pariſh-Churches, and left ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Gleanings, the ſmall Tythe, (the halt, blind and lame) to the Church for the continuance of the Service
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:43329:76"/> of God there, (which was now counted but cold and dull in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the more ardent and laſting Devotion of the <hi>Regular</hi>) and the maintenance of the <hi>Vicars.</hi> By that Name was the <hi>Pariſh-Prieſt</hi> call'd, who was left to perform the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and he was to live of theſe and the Offerings of the People, which were then conſiderable. The reſt of the Church-Revenues (which conſiſted in the great Tythes) were carried all away to theſe <hi>Fraternities.</hi> And then for to ſupply the want of Hoſpitality, ſome Feathers were left, a Church-Houſe, ſome ſmall Gift at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> or ſuch like were continued for ever. In a word, the Zeal towards this ſort of life was ſo great, from the time of the Conqueſt for about 150 Years, that the State was in danger to be ſwallowed up of the Church; and moſt of the Land of <hi>England,</hi> as well as the Revenues of the Church, turn'd all over to the Propriety of <hi>Monaſteries;</hi> ſo
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:43329:77"/> that they were forc'd to make <hi>the Statute of Mortmain in the Reign of</hi> Henry <hi>the Third to prevent it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>§. IX. <hi>The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and Methods of the ſame.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Pretences for theſe Aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were plauſible, which were the advancing the Service of God in a more Religious ſort of way, and the Salvation of Souls. The Tythes ſeem'd to be ſtill within the Church, tho' alienated from the firſt Place they were annext to: And the Portion which was ſtill left was thought ſufficient (toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Offerings and other Obventions) to maintain a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Perſon to officiate in the ſaid Church, for ſuch were the Clergy of thoſe Times. And yet this was a great Evil, and the cauſe of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as you ſhall hear preſently. For Time that depraves all things, made at laſt the very <hi>Monaſteries and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Orders publick Nuiſances.</hi> Thoſe holy Brothers and Siſters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated wholly from their Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſtrictneſs, and became abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:43329:77"/> for Pride, Idleneſs, and Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury. They were diſſolv'd in Eaſe, Riches, and Abundance. The cry of their Sins fill'd the Earth, and reach'd Heaven, and importun'd a final Diſſolution; which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly came upon them in the <hi>fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Century, and the Reign of</hi> Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry VIII. their final Suppreſſor. God nor Man cou'd endure their Wickedneſs no longer, but a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Viſitation prov'd their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. Some, as aſham'd of themſelves, were perſuaded to give up their Seals and Charters; others were trick'd out of them through Promiſes of Preferment, or Fears of Puniſhment; and thoſe that were obſtinate were diſſolv'd by <hi>Act of Parliament.</hi> And thus a multitude of goodly Buildings became rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Heaps, and a Place for wild Beaſts and unclean Birds. A Work perhaps not altogether ſo bad as it is repreſented; if they had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted the high Pleaſure of God, and Works of Piety and Charity,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:43329:78"/> with the Riches they found there, as they pretended, and the <hi>Acts of Parliament</hi> for their Diſſolution ſeem to intend: If alſo in their Diſſolution, each of their Acqueſts had return'd to their <hi>firſt Principle,</hi> the <hi>Lay-Gifts</hi> to them of the Laity, and the Church-Poſſeſſions to the ſeveral Churches from whence they had been taken. But that <hi>King</hi> and his Favourites (the Inſtruments of his Covetouſneſs and Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) divided the Spoils amongſt them; which (tho' ſo infinite) ſoon waſted away and came to nothing, and left the <hi>firſt Alienators</hi> as poor and as hungry as ever. Their Families are (moſt of them) diſſolv'd as the <hi>Religious Houſes</hi> were; and, like them, become a Heap and a Ruine. Thus the Tythes of ſo many Churches be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came loſt to all Purpoſes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and were (amongſt the other Spoils) carried away cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to ſerve Luxury and Pleaſure: Whence they muſt now never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:43329:78"/> again, but, <hi>like the ten Tribes,</hi> be loſt for evermore.</p>
               <p>Behold (<hi>Sir</hi>) the Effects of three contrary Principles, <hi>Devotion, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition,</hi> and <hi>Covetouſneſs. Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> built us up Churches, which ſtand ſtill as its Monuments; nor hath biting Time been able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour them. She endow'd as well as built them, and ſettled Perſons there to perform Divine Service to the Glory of God, and the Good of Mankind. <hi>Superſtition</hi> wou'd needs be meddling too, till ſhe had found ways to transferr them from the ſeveral Houſes of God to thoſe (commonly call'd Houſes) of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;</hi> and this under pretence of ſerving God more perfectly. But <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> diſcovered the Sham and Abuſe, and took thence occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſeize upon them to its own Uſe, and that of Pleaſures. Thus <hi>Avarice</hi> was too hard for all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion of our Fore-Fathers, and God is robb'd of his Tythes, and (in ſome Places) of his very Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:43329:79"/> And the Curſe annext to the <hi>Alienation</hi> has in ſome meaſure operated upon the <hi>Alienators,</hi> and I pray God that neither that nor his (mention'd <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 9.) may deſcend to the preſent <hi>Proprietors,</hi> or rather, <hi>Impropriators.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>§. X. <hi>The miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of ſuch Alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And now (<hi>Sir</hi>) before I part with this ſorrowful Inſtance of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Frailty, give me leave to lay before you the diſmal Conſequence of theſe <hi>Alienations,</hi> whereby the beſt <hi>Livings in</hi> England <hi>are impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated,</hi> and God's Portion become a <hi>Lay-Fee:</hi> Some of which are vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible at this Day, and are theſe that follow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The extream Poverty of<note place="margin">1. <hi>The Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty of the Clergy.</hi>
                  </note> ſuch of the Clergy who ſucceeded to thoſe remains of <hi>Benefices.</hi> The <hi>Gleanings</hi> were only left, a few <hi>ſmall Tythes,</hi> both troubleſome, vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atious, and invidious, to be colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, paid with regret and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings. The Lees that are to be ſqueez'd out with ſome Violence,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:43329:79"/> and oftentimes with the loſs of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: And the <hi>Law of them</hi> is ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective, that it is better to loſe all than remedy it. The Poor pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing, and the Rich what they pleaſe; and the <hi>Miniſter of God</hi> (their <hi>Spiritual Father</hi>) forc'd to ſtand by, ſee himſelf wrong'd by his Children, and dare not own it. The <hi>Tythe of Mint, Aniſe, and Cummin</hi> is reſerv'd ſtill, inſtead of that of the Staff of Life; and even this not to be enjoy'd without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions. And, indeed, there were two or three Things that in thoſe Days conſpir'd together to promote the Poverty and Miſery of many of the <hi>Clergy. Firſt,</hi> Their being diſpoſſeſt of their <hi>great Tythes</hi> that ſhou'd have ſupported them. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> Of the <hi>Offerings</hi> ſince. At the <hi>Appropriations</hi> of the <hi>Tythes to Monaſteries</hi> the <hi>Offerings</hi> were great and many. No Man (as I noted before) approached <hi>God's Altar</hi> but he offered liberally; and none made a Will but he gave ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:43329:80"/> to God and the Holy Church. And this was the reaſon why <hi>Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridges</hi> were left ſo bare in Tythes, becauſe of the Plenty of Offerings. But even theſe ſince the <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Religion,</hi> (which was a Bleſſing acknowledged with all due Thankfulneſs, and is no way guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of theſe Evils) which ſupported the Church for 300 Years, are now vaniſhed into Air, and ſunk almoſt to nothing, and by ſome counted <hi>Superſtitious,</hi> and by moſt unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. 'Tis true, the Law hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of them amongſt other Dues, and commanded their pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (which by the way hath changed the very Nature of the Thing) but then the Law refers to Cuſtom, which has <hi>melted them down</hi> to almoſt the ſmalleſt Summ payable; and that not to be reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered without great Charge and Trouble; ſo that in ſome Places they are forc'd to be wholly laid aſide. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The <hi>Abrogation of the Vow of Celebacy, and the Licence
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:43329:80"/> to Marry</hi> filled the Vicaridges full of ſmall Children, and that aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented their Cares and Poverty, and ſtill continues them. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if ever the Clergy had need of their <hi>Corn-Tythes</hi> to find them Bread, it was then when they had ſo Many Mouths to eat it. But the Church-men were ('tis like) then grown too proud and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaching, and Providence ſuffered a complication of Cauſes to meet and work their Humiliation; and ſo they did effectually, and have done ever ſince. Nor ſhou'd I grudge if this were all or the worſt Effect of <hi>Impropriations.</hi> But there be worſe that follow. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>§. XI. 2. <hi>Their loſs of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Contempt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> From hence proceeds their <hi>loſs of Authority,</hi> and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt they labour under. Our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies I know aſſign other <hi>Cauſes of the Contempt of the Clergy;</hi> but yet they cannot ſay but this is one, and no mean one too; and the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:43329:81"/> natural Effect of the ſmallneſs of their Eſtate. 'Tis true, St. <hi>Paul</hi> commands <hi>Titus</hi> not only to <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort but rebuke with all Authority;</hi> but thoſe were Times in which the Apoſtolick Men were endued with the <hi>Power of Miracles,</hi> and inflicting Diſeaſes and Judgments upon thoſe that ſlighted their Authority. They were delivered over to <hi>Satan</hi> for the chaſtiſing or deſtruction of the Body, that they might learn what it is to blaſpheme. But theſe mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Effects have long ſince left the Church, I preſume, ſince the time that the temporal Authority took upon her its defence: And what we do of this nature muſt be ordered according to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Prudence. For who dare in this irreligious Age undertake to reprove ſharply his <hi>Benefactor,</hi> which is the way to loſe him for ever. I know very well, the Scripture-Precepts do not conſider the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Condition of <hi>Paſtors,</hi> but oblige their Flocks to give them
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:43329:81"/> double Honour, and to know, <hi>i. e.</hi> acknowledge them and eſteem high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of them for their Work's ſake. But theſe Precepts may perhaps make ſome impreſſion upon the meek, humble, and conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſort of Chriſtians; and yet the <hi>Miniſter of God</hi> may fall under the Contempt and Deriſion of moſt of thoſe that yet profeſs themſelves to be ſo. And what a precarious Authority he can exerciſe over thoſe that feed and cloath him, is apparent by thoſe that do the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Offices</hi> in many great Mens Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, where they ſeem to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained moſtly (I fear) for State rather than Religion, and are more like Servants than <hi>Spiritual Fathers.</hi> And, in imitation of theſe, our Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try likewiſe admit them to bleſs the Meat, and then (unleſs they are <hi>Dignitaries,</hi> rich and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) to ſit at the lower end of their Tables, and prefer every <hi>Lawyer, Phyſician, Tradeſman,</hi> yea, and ſufficient <hi>Mechanick,</hi> to them.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:43329:82"/> And then what can <hi>Vicars</hi> and <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates,</hi> with a great many poor Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, expect from the wealthier ſort of Yeomen, who want the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, and Learning, and, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, the Civility of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? 'Tis true, the inferior <hi>Prieſts</hi> have a large Spiritual Authority; but what are Titles without Eſtates to ſupport their Credit? The <hi>Clergy</hi> have Titles, <hi>by Divine Right,</hi> great enough to make them envied, did not the meanneſs of many of their Fortunes make 'em deſpiſed. And ſhould a <hi>heavenly Angel</hi> deſcend down and dwell among Men, he muſt expect the ſame uſage. And therefore 'tis hard meaſure, firſt to take away their Eſtates, and then to object it to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>§. XII. 3. <hi>Their Depreſſion and Deje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Mind and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> From hence it is that ſo many of them are (the <hi>faeces Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li</hi>) the loweſt of the People; that they deſcend low in their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and are content to be thought ſo: For Poverty emaſculates the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:43329:82"/> Perſon, and makes him diſ-ſpirited and dejected. It brings him down into the Company, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the Vices, of the Vulgar. It invites him into the Society of Sots and Fools; and into a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partnerſhip of their Habits of Riot and Drinking. And hence it was that perhaps a <hi>memorable Perſon</hi> had his <hi>Maxim,</hi> That <hi>ſcandalous Places makes ſcandalous Miniſters.</hi> For Man is a ſociable Creature, and muſt aſſociate with ſome or other; and, if his Circumſtances will not permit him to chuſe that of the beſt, he is apt to take up with the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer: And by this means many an <hi>ingenious Man</hi> in his Youth loſes his good Parts in his Age, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lives all his Learning. And even the moſt <hi>innocent and unſpotted</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confin'd to a ruſtical ſort of Life, and wanting the Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Learned,</hi> ſhall contract a kind of Aſſimulation to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; he ſhall become rude and diffident, and not able to carry
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:43329:83"/> himſelf amongſt his Betters; and depreſs'd with Cares and Wants, muſt ſink down into the <hi>lower Orb of Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Stupidity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>§ XIII. 4. <hi>The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Poor,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> From hence I may (I hope without Vanity or Falſhood) aſſign one Cauſe of that Inhoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which produc'd a neceſſity of making Laws for the maintenance of the Poor. For the Tythes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divided from the Churches, to which they did of Right belong, and conferr'd on <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> and they diſſolv'd, there muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follow an increaſe of the Poor, who were wont to be reliev'd at their Gates. And accordingly we find few or no Laws made for the Relief of the Poor, or Repair of the Churches, while they were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors of that which enabled them for Hoſpitality. St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells his<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Timothy,</hi> That a <hi>Biſhop or Presbyter</hi> (for the word Ἐπίσκοπος in that place may ſignifie both) ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other things, be given to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:43329:83"/> Hoſpitality. And therefore he did preſume, that the Offerings of that Age, and the Tythes, Offerings, and Endowments of thoſe ſucceeding, wou'd enable him to be ſo. And ſuch I believe the Clergy then were till Covetouſneſs broke in upon them; and ſuch alſo I dare ſay the generality of thoſe few, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcap'd the fangs of Covetouſneſs, now are. As for others, they are forc'd to retrench Houſe-keeping and Expences, live meanly, and give little; becauſe they can ſpare but little from their own Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>§. XIV. 5. <hi>The neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion of God's Service.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>5. But the greateſt Evil of all is this, That hence it is that the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God becomes neglected, and the grateful Homage that we ſhou'd pay him daily is laid aſide. His Mercies are not kept in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and our Obligations are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, becauſe ſo ſeldom acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged. Amongſt God's own Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the <hi>Jews,</hi> there was the daily
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:43329:84"/> Adminiſtration, the <hi>Morning and Evening Sacrifice;</hi> and every <hi>Prieſt</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rub. <hi>In the End of the Service of the Church.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and Deacon</hi> is by the <hi>Rubrick of our Church</hi> enjoyn'd to uſe the Publick Prayers, Morning and Evening, publickly or privately (not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lett by Sickneſs or other urgent Cauſe.) And accordingly there is a Courſe of Service provided for every Day of the Year, both for <hi>Mattins</hi> and <hi>Evening Song.</hi> So it was anciently in the Church, and ſo it ſhou'd continue to this Day: That the Miniſter, <hi>the Mouth of the People,</hi> might ſupply their Defects, offer up their Prayers, and give a fit opportunity to thoſe that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout and cou'd ſpare time, to joyn with him. But this pious Cuſtom is now quite laid aſide. Men poſt over this Duty to the next Lord's-Day, or the next Holy-Day (where they are kept) and think it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make their Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments when they have nothing elſe to do. God is defrauded of his daily Sacrifice of Praiſe, and the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:43329:84"/> Church ſtands empty and uſeleſs all the Week. And indeed the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy for the moſt part cannot attend the daily Service for worldly Cares, and the neceſſary Proviſion for their Families; and they that can, have learn'd of the neceſſitous to be idle. They cannot (<hi>vacare Deo</hi>) wait upon God at his Houſe, but muſt divide their Service ſix parts to the Thoughts of this Life, and the ſeventh only to him. Such a daily Service muſt ſuppoſe a Man of ſufficient Eſtate, able in times of neceſſary Avocations to keep an Aſſiſtant, free from Cares, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thoſe about him who ſhall provide the daily Bread he asks at God's Hand, and who is the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of ſuch a Family, who may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him to the Houſe of Prayer, and give others a good Example: Whereas (as things ſtand now) we had need to Faſt as well as Pray continually; and, if we go to God's Houſe it muſt be by our ſelves without any Company. For, ſince
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:43329:85"/> the Wages have fallen ſo low, a part of the Duty proportional to it, hath been omitted; and God is robbed of his Tythes and Offerings, and of his Honour alſo. I do not ſay, that this deduction of Wages will juſtifie the neglect of Duty; but ſomething muſt be allowed to humane Frailty, and the want of Encouragement, and the neceſſities of Life. <hi>Who goes a Warfare at his own Charges? Who planteth a Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, and eateth not the Fruit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of?</hi> Or, <hi>who feedeth a Flock, and eateth not of the Milk of the ſame?</hi> 'Tis hard <hi>to muzzle the Ox that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out the Corn;</hi> or, expect that a ſort of Men ſhou'd plow and threſh without any expectation to be partakers of the Product. When the Reward was duly brought to the Altar, there cou'd not but be an Attendance there; but when there is nothing but Hunger and Nakedneſs to be found there, how many (or, rather, how few) will attend it? The Church puts us in
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:43329:85"/> mind of our Duty by commanding it, and yet thinks it not ſeaſonable to make any enquiry into the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it, leſt ſhe ſhould find too many Omiſſions and too many Reaſons for them.</p>
               <p>But further, from this diſuſe of<note place="margin">Whence proceeded the Opinion of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference, or rather, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeleſsneſs of Divine Service.</note> the daily Service proceeds an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference as to its Neceſſity, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect and ſlighting of it; yea, and a miſapprehenſion of the true Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it. For heretofore the Worſhip of God was thought to conſiſt in Prayers and Praiſes; and the <hi>Liturgy</hi> was look'd upon as the <hi>Standard</hi> and <hi>Magazine</hi> of both. But now this Notion of Worſhip is loſt or chang'd into <hi>Enthuſiaſtick Harangues,</hi> made up of canting Terms and Tones, to tickle the Ears and move the Paſſions of the Ignorant, who are apt to admire what they underſtand not, and be taken with a noiſie Zeal for God: Hence it is Preaching hath ſupplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prayer, and taken away all its Credit, and all its Neceſſity; yea,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:43329:86"/> and hath fermented it ſelf away to little elſe but Froth and Vapour. The truth is, <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> hath got into the Church, and is ready to juſtle out <hi>ſober Reaſon;</hi> extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Gifts the ordinary; and the pretended Spirit-ſpeaking in <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular</hi> Men, the Spirit which ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the <hi>Church.</hi> The ancient Methods of Religion will not now maintain its Miniſters; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Credit and Eſtate muſt <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>After the Example of the Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> &amp;c.</note> be gotten by pious Frauds, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to <hi>extraordinary Gifts and Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminations:</hi> All which, and many more evil Conſequences <note n="*" place="margin">As the increaſe of Fanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm and Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</note> (that I muſt not now take notice of) may be reduced to this Head, the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of the old rational way of Worſhip, and proceed from the ſame Cauſe, the <hi>depauperating of the Church by Impropriations.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>§. XV. 6. <hi>Plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and their Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> And laſtly, that I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion no more: If all theſe Evils be not enough, I have one more to add, which makes a greater noiſe
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:43329:86"/> than all, and is thought of worſe Conſequence, and that is <hi>Pluralities,</hi> which cannot be well remedied in reaſon without making every Place a <hi>competency.</hi> But ſo it is at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, (and have been ever ſince the times that the Church was robb'd of her Dues) that ſome <hi>two or three Cures of Souls</hi> cannot make one Competency for the ſupport of the <hi>Miniſter.</hi> So that there has been a neceſſity of diſpenſing with the <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Canons,</hi> not only to reward <hi>Merit,</hi> but to provide ſome <hi>labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prieſt</hi> to travel from one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and officiate in them. And if theſe <hi>Indulgencies</hi> were not gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Service of God muſt ceaſe for altogether in thoſe <hi>widowed Churches,</hi> as it doth now for ſome time, more or leſs. And tho' <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities</hi> may not be utterly unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in themſelves, yet they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways inconvenient if they cou'd be remedied. The <hi>Curates</hi> never of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiating ſo well, as for themſelves,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:43329:87"/> and not having that Authority as if they were Principals. But from this Cauſe is it, that <hi>Cures</hi> are ſo ſmall that they lie vacant without any <hi>Incumbent,</hi> and ſo are ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to ſome <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the <hi>Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge,</hi> by whom the Service is perform'd by halves; I mean, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as he can attend it, from that of his own Church; whilſt ſome are totally <hi>delapidated and dead of the Wounds they received in the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation.</hi> Whereas, if there was a Sufficiency in every Pariſh, (and if the great Tythes had not been ſeparated, there wou'd have been in moſt) there wou'd be little riding <hi>from Church to Church</hi> on Sundays, and very few <hi>Spiritual Polygamiſts.</hi> The Praiſes of God wou'd have been not only decent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but frequently, and daily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and offered up to God; and every Church wou'd be <hi>a Houſe of Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>§. XVI. <hi>The uſual Pleas for Impoveriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Clergy, and Objections againſt Works of Piety an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:43329:87"/>
               <p>I know very well, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe great Evils, it will be objected by the <hi>Adverſaries of the Clergy,</hi> That Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were poor, and ſo was the Church for the firſt 300 Years; during which time they preſerv'd Union and Communion; and, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Unity with themſelves, kept out <hi>Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Schiſms</hi> from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. That when the Churches became endow'd and rich, the Church-men became ſo Proud and Factious that they were ſoon hated. That their Luxury became great, and their Inſolence intolerable; and that the taking away theſe Superfluities was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for their Humiliation. That Piety conſiſts in Humility, and that is much advanc'd by Poverty: Whereas it has been obſerv'd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to a Proverb, <hi>Make the Prieſt rich, and you ſpoil him for ever:</hi> To all which I anſwer in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:43329:88"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Chriſt voluntarily choſe Poverty, as ſuitable to his Deſign of being crucified for the Sins of the World. And as for the Apoſtles, if they were Heirs of any Eſtates, they cou'd not have enjoyed them, becauſe of their continual Travels and Preaching. But then they were endow'd with that which was far better, and that was the Gifts of <hi>extraordinary Holineſs,</hi> and <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Power.</hi> Theſe ſupply'd all Wants, and drew to them the Love, Wonder, and Veneration of all Mankind, and made them Maſters of their Affections and Eſtates to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. They were received as <hi>Angels of God,</hi> and, if it had been poſſible and neceſſary, the Converts wou'd have <hi>plucked out their very Fyes</hi> to ſerve them. And then for the Primitive Church of the <hi>three firſt Centuries,</hi> they abounded in Gifts, Offerings, and occaſional Kindneſs; ſo that the Miniſtry liv'd as plentifully as their Circumſtances requir'd.</p>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:43329:88"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> 'Tis granted, that great Endowments make ſome Men Proud, Inſolent, and Factious, and ſo it did ſome of them. 'Tis too apparent, that every Man cannot manage Riches to the right uſes God intends it, yet I do not find that any Man is willing to part with it on that ſcore. And yet I cou'd be willing that every <hi>proud, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Clergy Man's Eſtate</hi> ſhou'd be confiſcated to the <hi>Laity</hi> during his life, upon condition that the ſame ſhou'd be obſerv'd on the other ſide. And yet I deny that this Charge is univerſally true; 'tis with the <hi>Clergy</hi> (and ſo has been) as with others. There have been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that have poſſeſt much, and yet have been Juſt, Liberal, Humble, and Merciful, and who did <hi>not truſt in uncertain Riches.</hi> And, if we may judge of the former Clergy in better Times, by thoſe we know in theſe worſe, we ſhall find that for the moſt part they were an obliging, humble, and hoſpitable
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:43329:89"/> ſort of Men. However, the abuſe of Things do not take away the right uſe of them; otherwiſe both <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Laity</hi> ſhould have been long ago ſtript of all. And, as for the Proverb, <hi>Of ſpoiling a Prieſt,</hi> &amp;c. it may or it may not be true, according to the different Nature or Inclination of the <hi>Reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pient.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Tho' Chriſtianity is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon Humility, yet Humility is not always the concomitant of Poverty. For I know as many Poor that are proud and inſolent as Rich. And tho' the Diſciples of our Lord were (for ſeveral Reaſons) moſt of 'em choſen out of the ordinary ſort of Men, yet ſome were Rich and Honourable; as <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea, Nicodemus, Nathanael, Zaccheus,</hi> and others. But this is according to the Meaſure of the Vertue of the Perſon; for otherwiſe Poverty in it ſelf is not deſirable. <hi>Give me neither Poverty nor Riches,</hi> ſaith the wiſe <hi>Agur.</hi>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:43329:89"/> Food convenient is beſt for all Men: And ſo much I wou'd have every <hi>Pariſh-Church</hi> endow'd with, and no more, that the Servant of God that dwells there may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and not call'd out by his Wants into other Places. And this may anſwer the Thing that I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to inquire into, <hi>viz. What</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 105.</note> 
                  <hi>may by Parity of Reaſon be thought a Sufficiency.</hi> That which enables<note place="margin">What muſt be judg'd a Sufficiency for every Pariſh-Prieſt.</note> 
                  <hi>God's Miniſter</hi> to perform the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Parts of his Duty without worldly Avocations, by which he is made capable to keep Hoſpitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, relieve the Poor, the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and Widow; viſit the Sick, attend the publick and private Worſhip of God, inſtruct the Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, comfort the Afflicted, charge the Rich to do his Duty as well as others, and <hi>rebuke with all Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> even the boldeſt vitious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; (I ſay) that which enables him to perform thoſe Parts of his Duty with aſſurance and confidence of Mind, is that <hi>Competency</hi> that I
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:43329:90"/> contend for: That which may nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make him inſult over the Poor or be afraid of the Rich, and live (in a word) <hi>above Contempt,</hi> and <hi>below Envy,</hi> is a <hi>Sufficiency.</hi> And ſo much I thought fit to ſay to this <hi>invidious Pretence,</hi> which looks more like a Prejudice than an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; and whoſe Authors wou'd fain be wiſer than God, and take new Meaſures for the Humiliation of the Clergy; but are, indeed, neither Friends to the Honour of God or Religion it ſelf.</p>
               <p>And now, to return to you after this long digreſſion (which was yet neceſſary to diſcover the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Avarice,</hi> to defraud God of his Worſhip, and his Miniſters of their Liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and then to appropriate the Tythes by ſuch Laws as ſhould eternally bar their return: The Conſequence of which is the cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Chriſtian daily Sacrifice of Praiſe altogether in ſome Places, and performing it by the halves in
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:43329:90"/> moſt: I ſay, to return to you) and to the Propoſition which I have, I hope ſufficiently confirm'd, by ſhewing that God himſelf hath thought fit by his own Alotments to provide plentifully for his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters under both Diſpenſations; and conſequently, That thoſe that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Service of God ought to be provided for with a Competen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſufficient for that purpoſe. And now I proceed to the Fifth and laſt; which is this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>§ XVII. Prop. 5. <hi>That it is the Duty of every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide ſuch a Competency for the Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of the Service of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 5. That it is the Duty of every Man, as far as he is able, to promote and ſettle the Worſhip of God; and to that End apply what he can of his earthly Talent to the providing ſuch a Competency for the Miniſters of Religion, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging them to their Duty.</p>
               <p>This was that Principle that built thoſe goodly Structures the <hi>Cathedrals,</hi> and other Parochial Houſes of Prayer, ſome of which
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:43329:91"/> remain to this Day, and that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow'd them with ſuch ample Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions for the maintenance of the Service of God, and thoſe that were devoted to it: This is that Principle which ſtood in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt Atheiſm, Covetouſneſs, and Sacrilege, and defended the Church as long as it was enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd; but is now laid aſide as an obſolete and unſeaſonable Doctrine, long ſince antiquated; and which (if reviv'd) might diſquiet the peaceable Poſſeſſion of thoſe that have purchaſed God's Inheritance, and raiſe up anew thoſe Scruples that have been now long ſince laid a ſleep, dead and buried. And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, this Principle wou'd reſtore the Service of God, together with the Tythes, or other Maintenance, unto all Churches, and provide fit Perſons to perform the one and receive the other; and therefore I ſhall endeavour to ſettle it from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Heads of Argument.</p>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:43329:91"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> From the Teſtimony of<note place="margin">This de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated. 1. From the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</note> Holy Scripture, both in the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament.</hi> And amongſt thoſe that offer themſelves, I ſhall accept only of one from either. The firſt is that of <hi>Prov. 3. 9, 10. Honour the Lord with thy ſubſtance, and with the firſt-fruits of thine increaſe; ſo ſhall thy Barns be filled with plenty, and thy Preſſes ſhall burſt out with new Wine.</hi> This is (not a <hi>Judicial</hi> or <hi>Ceremonial,</hi> but) a <hi>Moral</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and the Dictate of the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> which taught the <hi>Heathens</hi> to dedicate Things to God, and pay their Tythes and Firſt-Fruits to him under miſtaken Names, and to uphold a falſe Worſhip. It is as natural and reaſonable as Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude it ſelf, and therefore it reaches all Men and Times. Such are the <hi>Proverbs</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and ſuch is this Text. From whence we may obſerve: <hi>Firſt,</hi> That God may be honoured by our Subſtance, and by the Firſt-Fruits of our Increaſe: Which is done by applying it to
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:43329:92"/> the continuance of his Honour and Service. As was particularly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the <hi>Jews,</hi> and by the ſame<note place="margin">Deut. 26.</note> Equity reaches all other Nations. <hi>Secondly,</hi> We learn from theſe Words, That it is our Duty to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Honour of God with our Subſtance and Eſtates; as one of the Ends and Uſes for which he hath put it into our Hands, and intruſted it with us. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That a great and extraordinary Bleſſing is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed thereupon, and that we ſhall loſe nothing by ſuch <hi>Deodands.</hi> For <hi>our Barns ſhall be fill'd with Plenty, and our Preſſes even burſt with Wine.</hi> God will make a plentiful return, and reſtore with Advantage what we beſtow upon him. All this is contain'd in theſe Words, without the leaſt ſtretching them, and is the natural reſult of this Text, than which nothing can be more plain and evident, to eſtabliſh the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Propoſition. The ſecond Place is that of <hi>Gal. 6. 6. Let him that is taught in the word, communicate
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:43329:92"/> to him that teacheth in all good things;</hi> or, rather, (ἐν πᾶσιν ἀγαθοῖς) in all his Goods. Where we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that he that is taught (or, as we now call him, the <hi>Lay-Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> the <hi>Catechumen,</hi> according to the Original) is bound to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, (not contribute, for it is not an Alms, but a Due,) or, to exchange for the Spirituals his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals, even his beſt Things; to give him a ſufficient recompence of all that he poſſeſſes. It being but reaſonable that the Sower of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Things, in recompence of his Labour, ſhould reap the Temporal.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 11.</note> And if occaſional Recompences are due and acceptable, the ſettlement of our dedicated Things to the Support and Encouragement of Teachers for following Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt be more neceſſary, and more acceptable. And, having nam'd theſe two Texts, I need not deſcent upon our Lord's Maxim, <hi>Render to God the things that are God's;</hi> nor St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Argumentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:43329:93"/> for to eſtabliſh the Truth I plead for, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. nor need I ſtretch his ὅυτω καὶ ὁ Κύριος, &amp;c. Even ſo, or after the ſame manner, (that the Prieſts lived upon the Things and Endowments of the Temple and the Altar) hath Chriſt ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that <hi>thoſe that preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> I ſay, I need not, becauſe the former Texts are plain, cogent, and not to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded; and ſo are the latter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> From the Examples of<note place="margin">2. <hi>From the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God's People in all Ages.</hi>
                  </note> God's People in all Ages: The <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,</hi> the moveable Place of God's Worſhip, was made by the Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the whole Congregation, and that of their moſt precious Things; which they brought in ſo abundantly, that <hi>Moſes</hi> was forc'd to reſtrain 'em by Proclamation, <hi>Exod.</hi> 36. 5. And the great and glorious Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Joy, Envy and Wonder of the whole Earth, the ſettled Place of God's Service, and the Type and Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of the Holy Temple above:
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:43329:93"/> This wondrous and magnificent Building was the ſole Munificence of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> Kings of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael:</hi> It was repair'd by the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will Offerings of the People, and the poor Widow that threw in her whole Eſtate is recorded and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorated for the ſame, tho' it was but two Mites. And it was the Prince and People that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the daily Sacrifice, and their Offerings, Tythes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> that officiated there, and in the Synagogues and Oratories of the whole Nation.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Prieſt's Portion</hi> is not ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly commanded, but only the general Rules laid down, and the particulars left to prudent Piety. And if we look upon what they did, we ſhall find, that in ſome Places they offered up all to Works of Piety and Charity, as at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Acts</hi> 4. 35. Their Charity was ſo great that they ſeem'd to give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way even their own ſelves to the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:43329:94"/> Lord and his Apoſtles, as the Church of <hi>Macedonia, 2 Cor.</hi> 8. 5. And, indeed, in all Places in thoſe times of Zeal and Devotion, they were ſo abundantly Pious in reſpect of God, and ſo Charitable to the Poor, and took ſuch effectual Care for the Worſhip of God and his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, that there needed no De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Councils, or Laws of the Church or State, to force Men to build Churches or endow them,<note place="margin">Lib. de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trà ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos, <hi>p.</hi> 176.</note> (<hi>Nulla enim compulit neceſſitas, fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vente ubique religiosâ Devotione, &amp; amore illuſtrandi Eccleſias ultrò ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuante,</hi> ſaith <hi>Agobardus,</hi>) while the Flame of religious Devotion laſted, and the earneſt Deſire of building and endowing of Churches burned of its own accord: There needed no Laws or Canons to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn Men to pay their Tythes and Offerings, and to give to God's Treaſury: They did it of their own accord as far, and beyond what they were able. All the ſtately and magnificent Structures through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:43329:94"/> the Chriſtian World, that have eſcaped the Ruines of Time and Sacrilege, and their ample Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues: The decent Pariſh-Churches, and the <hi>Portions of Glebe</hi> and <hi>Tythe</hi> allotted to them by pious <hi>Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> (whoſe Names are recorded in Heaven, tho' loſt ſome of them on Earth) are ſufficient Evidences of this Truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> From the Equity of the<note place="margin">3. <hi>From the Equity of the Thing, and natural Reaſon, and from Men of all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions.</hi>
                  </note> Thing, and a Parity of natural Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. It cannot be imagin'd but that God ſhou'd take Care of his Honour; and we are told in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places that he is jealous of it, and that he will not give it to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Nor can it be thought but he hath the ſame Deſign in preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the World, and every Man's Eſtate and Properties, that he had in making it at firſt, which was for nothing but for the manifeſting his Glory and Goodneſs to created Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; ſo that it muſt be concluded that he is well pleaſed that Men <hi>ſhou'd praiſe him for his Goodneſs,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:43329:95"/> and declare the Wonders that he doth for the Children of Men.</hi> And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, that there ſhou'd be an Order of Men for that purpoſe, and Places where they might officiate and declare his Praiſes. Beſides, it is no reaſon we ſhou'd hold E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of God, and yet not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the ſame by Word and Deed. <hi>Homage and Fealty</hi> are but rational Returns amongſt our ſelves, the Foundation of our Titles and Right, and the Conditions upon which we poſſeſs what we have; and 'tis no leſs than Injuſtice and Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to deny them. And can we expect to poſſeſs his Gold and his Silver, and all the precious Products of his Earth, and yet allow him no Acknowledgments? Or, ſhall we imagine that he was careful of his Honour heretofore under the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law, and yet has wholly forgot it amongſt us? No, certainly, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſeems to be written in every Man's Heart, and to be part of the Law of Nature. Hence it is, that
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:43329:95"/> even the <hi>Heathens</hi> (as well as the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had ever, and) have ſtill their <hi>Temples, Oratories, Oracles, Prieſts,</hi> and the Places and Miniſters of Religion, and theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed plentifully, and, in ſome Places, magnificently provided for. And tho' they miſtook the Object, the true God, yet they agreed with all others, that <hi>he was to be worſhipped.</hi> The Chriſtians in all Ages, ſince our Lord's Aſcention, had their <hi>Orato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> Places of Divine Service, and (as ſoon as they cou'd for Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) their Churches and Houſes of Prayer; yea, and thoſe beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, inrich'd, and endow'd with plentiful Revenues: Thus they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for many <hi>Centuries,</hi> till the Devil found out the way to impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſh them, under pretence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. And (what ought to be taken likewiſe into Conſideration, and ſhame the luke-warm and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who are content to ſerve God with a cheap Religion, and
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:43329:96"/> that which coſt them nothing) the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> themſelves, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Denomination they are, or by what Sect or Name diſtinguiſhed, think themſelves oblig'd to build <hi>Meeting-Houſes,</hi> (ſeeing they muſt not, nor can take poſſeſſion of our Churches;) nor can I blame them, it being the natural Conſequence of their Principles, which cannot, it ſeems, joyn with ours in our worſhip of God. And without doubt (if Times and Circumſtances wou'd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low) they wou'd do what was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the maintaining and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tling their Service in the ſaid Places. And, in the mean time, they raiſe <hi>voluntary Contributions</hi> for the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of their <hi>Teachers,</hi> in propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (as 'tis ſaid) ſuperior to what we of the Church of <hi>England</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy by Law of the Eſtates that are ſtill left us. And while thoſe of our Communion leave the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> to make ſhift with the preſent Settlements, tho' never ſo ſmall, (which are the Remains of our <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:43329:96"/> Piety,</hi> and no thank to us, for it has been demonſtrated, that we pay nothing of our own to the Pariſh-Prieſt, but our Offerings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) whilſt they, I ſay, ſeldom will be perſuaded to add any thing to their ſmall Stipends, unleſs they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their Duties with an additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sermon, or the like, the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters</hi> (all but the <hi>Quakers</hi>) pay <hi>Scot</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> and their <hi>Tythes,</hi> and yet can find Money to pay their <hi>Teachers,</hi> and diſcharge the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſuper-numerary Expences of their Communion. And this I note to the ſhame of thoſe of our own Communion, that are bred up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the beſt Church in the World, and yet are moſt unworthy of that Privilege.</p>
               <p>The Summ of all is this; and<note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cluſion from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes.</note> from the Premiſſes I wou'd inferr this Concluſion: Every Man ought, to the utmoſt of his Ability, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the maintenance and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the Worſhip of God,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:43329:97"/> which, by reaſon of the ſmalneſs of the <hi>ſettled Revenue,</hi> is in ſome Places quite intermitted, and in others perform'd by halves; ſo that the <hi>Adminiſtrator</hi> of God's Service, and his Dependents, might live plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and be able to attend the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his Calling without neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitous Avocations. Then God wou'd be duly ſerv'd, his Miniſter be rever'd, his Authority be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, Hoſpitality and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty maintain'd, the Poor reliev'd, and <hi>Publick Prayers</hi> wou'd be made daily for himſelf and them, while the Devout wou'd have the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of the Hours of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Then every <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter</hi> wou'd be the Husband of one Church as well as one Wife, nor wou'd there be more need of <hi>Pluralities</hi> of <hi>Parſonages</hi> than of <hi>Wives:</hi> And whether theſe are not Bleſſings conſiderable, and worth the deſire and ſtriving af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I leave you and all the World to judge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>§. XVIII.</head>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:43329:97"/>
               <p>And now I have done, when I have anſwered the Pleas that Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice and Selfiſhneſs may put in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Duty I plead for, and made ſome fit Applicatory Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. And,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> It will be ſaid, That this<note place="margin">The ſeveral Pleas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Works of Piety con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd and anſwer'd.</note> is a <hi>Project</hi> too large for Practice, and a burthen too heavy to carry on. It wou'd require the Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional of 100 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> in ſome Places, and in moſt <hi>Vicaridges</hi> ſome. And this is impracticable at any time, and unſeaſonable (becauſe impoſſible) in this time of ſcarci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Money, and <hi>great Taxes.</hi> That ſuch Additions wou'd render the <hi>Clergy</hi> proud and idle, and might in any Revolution of Government be chang'd to advance Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and perhaps <hi>Popery</hi> it ſelf; at leaſt be diverted from the Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Benefactor. To all which I ſhall anſwer in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:43329:98"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> For the greatneſs of this Work, let it take up what time it will, ſo it were begun, and tho' a Sufficiency cannot be provided in an Age or two, yet this can be no Excuſe to a Man of good Eſtate for not contributing ſomething to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it. Who knows how pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent and effectual a good Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may be, and whoſe Hearts God will raiſe up to repair the Breaches of his Houſe upon ſo good a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent?</hi> But, if no Body follows you, yet your Reward ſhall not be deny'd you; and if they do, it will be augmented by their Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, while yours was the cauſe. But I cannot ſee the impoſſibility of ſuch a Work, if Men were but willing and in Earneſt. For we ſee many Places contribute for <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> beſides their Dues to the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter</hi> and <hi>Impropriator.</hi> The <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed</hi> in <hi>France</hi> (till this late Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution) gladly paid their Tythe to the <hi>Curate</hi> of their Pariſh, and
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:43329:98"/> yet maintain'd their own <hi>Paſtors.</hi> And the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> (whether wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly or no) do the ſame, and yet they are the thriving part of the Nation; and who knows but God may bleſs their well-intended (tho indeed needleſs) Piety? Now what is done from Year to Year may be ſettled for Futurity, and were the Members of our Church as Induſtrious and Zealous to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it, as the <hi>diſſenting Party</hi> are to pull it down; and as good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands to ſave, as they are, I do not ſee but Additions may be made to many ſmall Places, and a Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſame for future Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. 'Tis but to abate ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from our Pride, Senſuality, Luxury, Riot, Drunkenneſs, and other chargeable and expenſive Crimes, and mind our own Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and God's Glory, and the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty wou'd be ſoon removed; and if the Thing cou'd not be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in one Age, yet there might
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:43329:99"/> be a Foundation laid for the finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> But it is further ſaid, That ſuch an Addreſs is at this time unſeaſonable, for, that <hi>War</hi> ſeems to be entail'd upon us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But I may anſwer in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Words; <hi>From whence come Wars? Come they not from our Luſts?</hi> And ſhall theſe hinder the payment of our <hi>Quit-Rent</hi> to God, our Chief Lord, or our Homage to our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker? But this may <hi>be done, and the other left not undone.</hi> And the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State of all the <hi>diſſenting Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> in the World evinces ſo much, who bear their part of all ordinary and extraordinary Taxes, ſupport their Families, and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute plentifully to their <hi>Teachers</hi> beſides. An Example (be ſure) of the feaſibility of the Thing, and a Pattern to all the Profeſſors of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:43329:99"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Preſumption of the Pride and Inſolence of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men hath been conſidered already. Alas, there is no danger of that in theſe Times, and when that is like to be, let the Benefactors ſtay their Hands, or impoſe ſuch Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that may bridle them. But then,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> For the ſuppos'd Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of the alteration of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as it is but a bare Poſſibility, ſo the piouſly inclin'd may well leave that to God, and truſt him with the Event. Give then with an upright Heart and a right Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and leave the Iſſue to Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, who will take Care for his own Glory. And if the Gift ſhould chance to be miſ-imploy'd, yet that, being not our Fault, cannot in the leaſt leſſen the Reward. But this Objection wou'd hinder all good Works, and rob the Church and Poor of what is left 'em, and
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:43329:100"/> therefore I diſmiſs it as impertinent, and of miſchievous conſequence, both to Religion and Charity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>§. XIX. <hi>A general and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And now (<hi>Sir</hi>) becauſe the World ſhall not know your Name, Condition, Character, or Perſon, give me leave to make the Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in general to all ſorts of Men, and to thoſe eſpecially whom God hath made capable of Works of Piety and Charity: Wherein, tho' I may ſeem to leave you, yet I may perhaps meet you <hi>incognito,</hi> and ſpeak to you ſtill under one Denomination or another. And,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let me addreſs my ſelf of<note place="margin">1. <hi>To the Noble, Rich, and Wealthy.</hi>
                  </note> all the Rich and Wealthy, amongſt whom many are dignified and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed with great Names and Titles. Our bleſſed Lord ſeems to paſs a hard Sentence upon rich Men, when he makes their Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as difficult as <hi>for a Camel to paſs through the Eye of a Needle,</hi> which
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:43329:100"/> one wou'd think was impoſſible. The reaſon is, the great Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that is in humane Nature to become proud and faſtidious by the flattery and falſe meaſures of Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure. <hi>They that will be rich</hi> (ſaith his Apoſtle) <hi>uſually fall into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and a ſnare, and into many foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and hurtful Luſts, that drown men in diſtraction and perdition.</hi> They are put in a dangerous Poſt, and have a great Duty upon them, and muſt make a greater Account than other Men. And yet amongſt all theſe lov'd and courted Dangers, they have this great Advantage, that they are capable of doing more Good, and ſerving God to more and better Purpoſes than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men. Theſe Men are poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the earthly <hi>Mammon,</hi> and with that which is uſually an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Unrighteouſneſs may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure everlaſting Habitations. But then this is not to be done but by Works of Piety and Mercy; by
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:43329:101"/> giving God and the indigent Part of Mankind their due; <hi>by loving of Mercy, and walking humbly with</hi> (that is worſhipping) <hi>God.</hi> For there is a way of making Returns to Heaven, of paying in worldly Goods and receiving Glory, of laying in <hi>Bank</hi> and <hi>Fund</hi> here ſuch a Stock of good Works that ſhall produce a Reward infinite both in Duration and Quantity. And this is the true, beſt, and prudenteſt way of <hi>Merchandizing.</hi> I will not ſay, that a Man may purchaſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and barter for a Crown of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for that ſeems to be the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of an equivalent, but ſo it is, God has made (by a free Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe) Heaven and its Joys the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of good Works, and of thoſe that we do, which are hardly our own. So that there is a way open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Man to advance himſelf in the World to come, as well as in this. And as Riches is the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool to Honour (for who ever
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:43329:101"/> heard Poverty courted or honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) in this World, ſo it may be in the next, and (if us'd as it ought) will be certainly. Every tranſient Act of Piety and Mercy is recorded above, and hath a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward aſſign'd for it there. But thoſe that are fix'd for a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and that benefit ſucceeding Subjects, continually operating for the good of Mankind: Thoſe, I ſay, (that I may borrow and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the Inſtance in the Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the former Letter) bring af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them an increaſe of Glory eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Day, anſwerable to the Good they do. Thus a <hi>Founder</hi> of a <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege</hi> or <hi>Hoſpital</hi> muſt needs receive Acceſſions of Reward, agreeable to the mighty Good of Education and Edification of thoſe bred up and maintained in it. And the <hi>Founder</hi> of a Church to the Honour of God, (as he was the Cauſe, ſo he) muſt receive the Reward of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that is exhibited there during
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:43329:102"/> the time of its ſtanding. And who knows but that this was one cauſe of the Diſſolution of the <hi>Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> and <hi>Abbeys,</hi> becauſe by their Wickedneſs they were become Dens of Thieves inſtead of Religious Houſes, and ceaſed to yield any more Glory to God, or Reward to their <hi>Founders</hi> and <hi>Benefactors.</hi> You have then (<hi>Sirs</hi>) an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity that courts you to make your ſelves Happy, and convey a Bleſſing with the main of your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate to your Poſterity. And here I cannot but admire, and at the ſame time upbraid your unaccount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and extravagant Love to your Sons and Daughters; to your Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews or Nieces; to your Heirs, be they of your own Family or no; for whom you ingroſs all, and with that Application, that you cannot ſpare any thing for God and Charity, nay (ſome of you, I fear) for your own ſake; and ſo you run up an infinite Score, and
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:43329:102"/> an apparent hazard of being ſhut out of Heaven for your Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty's ſake. And your Care of theſe is ſo great, that you fear not to make your ſelves miſerable to all Eternity hereafter, (and ſome of you here alſo) to make them, as you conceive, Happy: For ſo doth the Proverb pronounce that Son whoſe Father goes to the Devil for him. Conſider (<hi>Sirs</hi>) that you were not ſent hither to eat and to drink, and to beget your like, and provide for them, that they alſo may do ſo after your deceaſe; but to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God here, and to be glorified by him (or elſe to be miſerable) to Eternity. The time of Diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and Account is coming on apace. And tho' you at preſent put from you the evil Day, while you deſpiſe and tread upon all but your ſelves and thoſe of your own Degree; yet know, that it comes, and that ſwiftly, and every Minute of Pleaſure and Jollity, of Cares,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:43329:103"/> Fears, of Fraud or Violence, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Day of Feaſting and Night of Mirth, brings the fatal time on; wherein you muſt be ſtrip'd of your <hi>Titles</hi> and <hi>Acqueſts</hi> of <hi>Honour,</hi> and leave all theſe your goodly <hi>Buildings, Gardens, Parks,</hi> and <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings,</hi> your Friends and Flatterers, and the Partners of your Loves and Luſts, and be carried all alone into the unknown State of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, whither your good and evil Works will follow; thoſe to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, theſe to accuſe, and what ſhall become then of him who hath whole Multitudes of the latter and none of the former? Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber then the Counſel of the wiſe King; <hi>Withhold not Good from them to whom it is due, when it is in the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 3. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Power of thy Hand to do it:</hi> Or, that of the Apoſtle; <hi>To do Good</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>and to Communicate forget not, for with ſuch Sacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>§. XX. 2. <hi>To the Impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:43329:103"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> But amongſt the Great and Rich there are not a few that have a more particular Obligation to the reſtoring and perpetuating the Service of God, becauſe their Predeceſſors were the Inſtruments of the intermiſſion of it; I mean the <hi>Impropriators.</hi> Theſe are moſt of them Men of conſiderable E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and many of great Vertue and Piety in all other things but this; and <hi>in this the Lord Pardon thy Servants,</hi> &amp;c. Any thing but parting with their Freeholds for God's ſake, tho they anciently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd to him, and he never yet quitted his Title to them. To theſe may I be ſo bold with all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility as to addreſs them to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that they are mightily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the clearing two or three Queſtions. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Whether Tythes are due to God, and to thoſe that execute his Service (<hi>jure Divino</hi>) by a Divine Right? That they are
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:43329:104"/> ſo is the common Opinion of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, Canoniſts, Civilians;</hi> yea, and the <hi>Common Lawyers</hi> too. Only<note place="margin">Doct. &amp; Stud. l. 2. c. 55. p. 164.</note> theſe latter diſtinguiſh of Tythes, which they ſay may be conſidered <hi>quoad decimam partem,</hi> or <hi>quoad ſuſtentationem ſufficientem Cleri vel</hi>
                  <note place="margin">19 Eliz. in B. R.</note> 
                  <hi>Miniſtrorum Dei,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That the exact Tenth Part, is not due of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right, but ſo much as is ſufficient to maintain the Miniſter of God.</hi> Now, tho' this Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be little leſs than a Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, (for if Tythes are due <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> the Tenth Part muſt be ſo, being both the ſame;) yet from theſe Determinations of the Judges we gain this Point, That a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petency of Tythes ought to be left to every Church for the neceſſary Suſtentation of the <hi>Prieſt</hi> that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiates there; and this Part is due <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> and conſequently can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſeparated by any humane Law. And if ſo, thoſe that quite beggar'd the Church (by carrying
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:43329:104"/> away all, or the beſt Part) were by the Common Law no leſs than <hi>Church-Robbers,</hi> and guilty of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege; and the preſent Poſſeſſor of Tythes is bound to reſtore ſo much as is neceſſary to maintain the Worſhip of God in that Church, from whence they were taken, or elſe he is guilty of the ſame Crime, and becomes anſwerable for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion of the Service of God during his time; which is no leſs than robbing of God of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and is the worſt kind of Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Whether things conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to God's Service with the greateſt Solemnities, and the ſtricteſt Tyes imaginable, may (upon a preſum'd Abuſe) be alienated and converted to common Uſes, and that by any humane Authority?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Wherein conſiſted <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzar</hi>'s Crime, and why might he
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:43329:105"/> not eat and drink out of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels once conſecrated, (but now long ſince carried out of the Temple by his Grand-Father) when the Temple it ſelf was deſtroyed, and the Service thereof at at end?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Suppoſing the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all this; yet, whether in common Equity it can be thought pleaſing to God to ſerve our Luſts and Pleaſures with that which was once dedicated to his Service on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? And yet at the ſame time know that his Worſhip ceaſes for want of it in ſome Places altogether, and in others it is perform'd but once in a Week, Fortnight, or Month, as in many Places in this Kingdom; and in ſome not at all: And all this for want of a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Settlement for one to perform it. And whether thoſe that eat and drink thoſe once Holy (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe dedicated) Things, and thoſe that are capable of making ſuch
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:43329:105"/> Proviſions <hi>de novo</hi> (and do it not) are not the occaſions of theſe O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, and ſo lovers of their Pleaſures more than lovers of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Whether theſe <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> might not only promote the Honour of God, but reform ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Abuſes and Neglects in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, by returning back ſome of the Churches ancient <hi>Demeſns,</hi> or dedicating ſome Equivalent, under ſuch Conditions and Limitations, that might oblige the <hi>Miniſter</hi> to frequency and fervency of Duty, over and above what the Law can compel him to, upon peril and loſs of ſuch Endowments, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new <hi>Founders</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> and Reſtorers of God's Glory? And, if this may be done, then whether they are not bound in Conſcience to do it? Theſe are weighty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, which nearly concern all (<hi>Impropriators</hi> eſpecially) of what Degree ſoever they be; and I pray
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:43329:106"/> God to ſet it home to their Hearts, that they may make ſome ſort of Satisfaction for the Sacrilege of the firſt <hi>Alienators,</hi> and that the Curſe of the wrong'd <hi>Donors</hi> may never reach them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>§. XXI. <hi>To thoſe that have no Children to provide for.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Third,</hi> Let me next addreſs my ſelf to certain Perſons of Eſtate and Quality in this Nation, who are qualified and (as it were) mark'd out for ſuch a Work. Such are they to whom God never gave any Children, (the neceſſary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for whom we make our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Plea for our Selfiſhneſs,) or from whom he hath taken moſt or all, (and ſo conſequently the Charge appropriated to them,) Men that have plentiful Eſtates, but want Heirs of their Bodies, and ſo are forc'd to ſeek for them amongſt the other Branches of their Family; or, adopt ſome one of their Name amongſt thoſe that are no Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and oftentimes beſtow all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one that wants it not; or, that
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:43329:106"/> ſhall waſte all when they are dead, and wiſh them ſo, while living. <hi>Fond Men!</hi> that refuſe God for their Heir, and his Service, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow their Eſtates upon, even then when they can hold it no longer! What might not ſuch a Man do? Why, he might buy Heaven with Earth, and a Crown of Glory with this worldly Traſh: He might pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe an everlaſting Habitation with the <hi>Mammon of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs,</hi> even then when he muſt uſe it no longer: He might raiſe to himſelf an everlaſting Monument, and a Name more durable than that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven in Braſs or Marble! And yet loſe all thoſe precious Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, and throw away all he hath upon ſome Kinſman afar off, or ſome Nieces Husband, or ſome Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy leſs deſerving, tho' nearer in Relation; one who ſhall uſe it to the Satisfaction of his Luſts and Appetites, and the diſhonour of himſelf and his Maker. Doth not ſuch a Man ſeem to be deſign'd
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:43329:107"/> by Heaven to promote the Honour of his Maker? his way is prepar'd, all Obſtacles are remov'd, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf adapted to ſo great and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Work. And ſhall a vain <hi>Name,</hi> a pompous <hi>Retinue,</hi> a great <hi>Table,</hi> and a company of debauch'd <hi>Servants,</hi> eat him up living? And ſome politick <hi>Relation</hi> ſweep all away when he dies, and ſo defeat himſelf of the Product of all the Good that he might do, or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample that he might give to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? Or, doth ſuch a Man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that God ſhou'd give him a plainer Indication of his Will, than to take away all Objections, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able him to do ſome conſiderable Good? He acts with Man by ſuch Methods as are conſiſtent with his freedom of Will; he gives us op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, and then leaves us to make our Election. I wou'd not here (nor any where elſe) be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtood. I think the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples upon which theſe Diſcourſes are built, will make no Man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:43329:107"/> to his <hi>Relations,</hi> or himſelf; but this is all I ſay, That if every Man that is Childleſs (or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe enabled) wou'd but leave God a <hi>Legacy</hi> worthy of him when he dies, and lay up the <hi>Tenths</hi> of his increaſe while he liv'd for his Uſe, it wou'd ſoon make every <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> a Competency, and every Church a <hi>Houſe of Praiſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <head>§. XXII. 4. <hi>To the Biſhops, Dignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and others of the Clergy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Nor muſt I paſs by my <hi>Lords</hi> the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> the <hi>Dignitaries,</hi> and other the richer Part of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> but humbly repreſent to them the Repairing of the Houſe of God, the proping up of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining Church, and that Service that muſt uphold them. They are fed, nouriſhed, and ſometimes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd by the Devotion of others to God's Altar: To that many owe their Living and the Riches that they have gotten; and 'tis all the reaſon in the World, that their Relations ſhou'd not ſweep away all, but that ſomething ſhou'd be
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:43329:108"/> return'd back again to increaſe that <hi>Treaſury</hi> from whence they have received all. The <hi>Policy of the Church of</hi> Rome forbids the Marriage of their <hi>Clergy,</hi> and (if I am not miſtaken) makes the Church their Heir. Our Church obliges us to neither. Not to the firſt, becauſe contrary to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures and Reaſon; not to the latter, becauſe 'tis contrary to Nature for Men to paſs by their own Children and leave them Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars. But tho' the Church obliges to neither, yet ſhe cannot but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend both, or either, to thoſe to whom this Gift is given. Happy is that Man that is therefore <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married, that he may care for the things of the Lord</hi> whilſt he lives, and provide for them when he dies. But, woe is me! Can there be any ſuch Men amongſt us, whoſe deſires of Pluralities and Riches are inſatiable, who take no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Care but to ſhear their Flocks, and gather the good Things of the
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:43329:108"/> Altar, and lay them up in ſtore, as if againſt an approaching Famine? That leave the Cares of their Flocks to their poor <hi>Curates,</hi> whoſe Faces they grind amongſt the reſt, and will not allow them to live, tho' they bear <hi>the Burthen of the Day?</hi> That leave them the Care of great Pariſhes, to attend the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Service, and themſelves live at Eaſe, reap all the Profit, and allow them not the twentieth Part? I am aſham'd to ſay that there is ſuch a Man. For, next to the Sot, the Senſualiſt, the Drunkard, and the Debauch'd, the covetous and cruel <hi>Clergy-man</hi> is the moſt unſeemly and unbecoming Object, and the very Contradiction of his Calling. And let me humbly propoſe one thing: Would every <hi>Biſhop</hi> once in his whole Life do ſome eminent Work of Piety, it wou'd not only be Exemplary to ſtir up others, but wou'd have been conſiderable by this time; and if every rich <hi>Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> (who has either no Children,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:43329:109"/> or whoſe Charge is moderately provided for) wou'd but return to the Church ſome Part of thoſe Alms that he hath receiv'd at her Hands, (and 'tis all the reaſon in the World it ſhou'd be ſo,) it wou'd be the like. And as for thoſe of this Order that are utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable to add any thing but their Prayers to ſo good a Work, I ſhall entreat them that they do not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it. I mean, that by the ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Lives, and the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious Diſcharge of their Duty, they wou'd walk worthy of ſuch a Bleſſing, encourage Piety and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and ſhew that that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſtill to the Church, is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted or thrown away upon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <head>§ XXIII. 5. <hi>To all in general.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Let me apply my ſelf to all Men in general, that they wou'd take that Account of their Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardſhip (that they muſt make at the laſt Day) into Conſideration, and weigh well the beſt that can commonly and generally be made,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:43329:109"/> even by the beſt of Men, (which,<note place="margin">The beſt Account that can be made gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally at the laſt Day, and its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency.</note> as I noted in the beginning of the firſt Letter) is this; That they have been good Husbands, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully advanc'd (or, at leaſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd) their Talent, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fraud or Violence. That theſe have ſupported themſelves and their Dependants with the Rents and Iſſues of the ſame, during their Lives, and, when they died, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd them carefully to their Heirs and Aſſigns; but whether they were left to wiſe Men or Fools they knew not; or, whether they are like to be imployed to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God or the Devil, they have made no Proviſion. But to what purpoſe they have liv'd, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God or Man has been benefitted by their Lives they cannot ſhew, no more than they can <hi>one Acre</hi> or <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacy</hi> for the Uſes of Piety and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. That as they have wrong'd, ſo they have done good to no Man: They have only poſſeſſed their own, and only themſelves, and their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:43329:110"/> ſelves and neareſt Relations have reaped the Benefits of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is the beſt Account that moſt Men can give, (and how few are there that can give ſo good?) and yet I leave it even to the Judgments of theſe <hi>Accountants</hi> themſelves, Whether an honeſt and wiſe <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> may not give up a better? Or, whether the unprofitable Servant in the Goſpel did not give up the ſame? And yet we read its Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward was no leſs than utter Darkneſs, <hi>where there is weeping and gnaſhing of Teeth;</hi> from which <hi>good Lord deliver us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But how much better and more<note place="margin">A better way of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting with God, and the concluſion of the whole.</note> comfortable wou'd it be when we come to die, if we cou'd ſay to God as the religious <hi>Iſraelite</hi> was taught to ſay, (in the end of the third Year, uſually call'd the Year of Tything, when he had given the <hi>Levite,</hi> the Stranger, the Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and the Widows, their Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,) <hi>Deut. 26. 13. I have brought
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:43329:110"/> away the hallowed things, [viz.</hi> That which I ſet apart, and dedicated to thy Service,] <hi>out of mine own houſe,</hi> [to thine, and there according to my Vows] <hi>I have diſtributed them,</hi> [ſome] <hi>to the Levite,</hi> [for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of thy Service; ſome to Works of Charity,] <hi>to the Stranger, the Fatherleſs, and the Widow, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy Commandments, which thou (O Lord) haſt commanded me: I have not tranſgreſſed thy Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor forgotten them,</hi> &amp;c. And [I cannot but expect thy Bleſſing upon what I have left, to deſcend with it down to my Heirs, <hi>&amp;c.] Look down therefore from thy Holy Habitation, and bleſs thy People, and the Land which thou haſt given me,</hi> &amp;c. When we can teſtifie before our Judge, that we have not altogether ſerv'd our Pleaſures, nor our Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites, with that which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to our Charge, but to the utmoſt of our Powers have advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Honour of our God, and the Good of our Neighbour with
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:43329:111"/> it during our Lives, and when we were to leave the World, that we likewiſe ſecur'd ſomething for the Service of Piety and Charity, ſo that it ſhall not be in the Power of our Heirs to alienate it.</p>
               <p>This and only this can Comfort and Support the timorous Soul when it is brought before its Judge, and aſſure it of a welcome. It wou'd not only enſure us of Heaven, but of a proportional increaſe of its Joys, according to the Effects of our good Works. It would likewiſe aſcertain an everlaſting Name up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, and build us up a <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> more durable than that of the dead deceitful <hi>Braſs</hi> or <hi>Marble;</hi> or, thoſe living, but periſhing ones, of Sons and Daughters; whilſt we receive the Applauſes of future as well as preſent Ages, and thoſe now unborn ſhall hereafter riſe up and call us <hi>bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:43329:111"/>
               <p>And may you (<hi>Sir</hi>) be partaker of this Bleſſedneſs which is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of Piety and Charity, both on Earth here, and in Heaven here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. And ſo I return to take my Leave of you, and to beg your candid Interpretation of any Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in either Letter, and your Pardon for any Miſtake in both, ſeeing I intended them for your Service, and they were written for your Uſe, and at your Command. For I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
                  <signed>Yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:43329:112"/>
            <head>Books printed for <hi>Walter Ket<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop's Head,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>INſtitutiones Grammaticae Anglo-Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onicae, &amp; Meſo-Gothicae. Auctore Georgio Hickſio, Eccleſiae Anglicanae Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytero, 4to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Chriſt. Waſii Senarius, ſive de Legibus &amp; Licentia veterum Poetarum, 4to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Miſna, Pars Ordinis primi Jeraim titul. Septem. Latinè vertit &amp; Commentario illuſtravit Gulielmus Guiſinus: Accedit Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis Maimonidis Praefatio, Edvardo Pocockio Interprete, 4to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Joannis Antiocheni Cognomento Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lala Hiſt. Chronica, è M. S. Bibliothecae Bodleianae. Praemittitur Diſſertatio de Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thore. Per Humph. Hodium, D. D. 8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Biſhop <hi>Overal</hi>'s Convocation Book 1606, concerning the Government of God's Catholick Church, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the whole World, <hi>4to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. True Conduct of Perſons of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Tranſlated out of <hi>French. 8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. A Treatiſe relating to the Worſhip of God, divided into Six Sections: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning, <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Nature of Divine Worſhip. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The peculiar Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Worſhip. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The true
<pb facs="tcp:43329:112"/> Worſhippers of God. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Aſſiſtance requiſite to Worſhip. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The Place of Worſhip. <hi>Sixthly,</hi> The ſolemn Time of Worſhip. By <hi>John Templer,</hi> D. D. <hi>8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. A Defence of revealed Religion, in ſix Sermons, upon <hi>Romans</hi> 1. 16. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is clearly and plainly ſhewn, That no Man can poſſibly have any real Ground or Reaſon to be aſhamed of Chriſtianity. By <hi>Henry Halliwell,</hi> M. A. and Vicar of <hi>Cowfold</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> 80.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Miſcellanies, in five Eſſays. 1. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Office of a Chaplain. 2. Upon Pride. 3. Upon Cloaths. 4. Upon Dealing. 5. Upon General Kindneſs. The four laſt by way of Dialogue. By <hi>Jeremy Collier,</hi> A. M. <hi>8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. Myſteries in Religion vindicated: Or, the Filiation, Duty and Satisfaction of our Saviour aſſerted, againſt <hi>Socinians</hi> and others: With occaſional Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on ſeveral late Pamphlets. By <hi>Luke Milbourn,</hi> a Presbyter of the Church of <hi>England. 8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. A Diſcourſe concerning the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Man, both in his natural and political Capacity, both as he is a ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Creature and Member of a Civil Society: With an Examination of ſome of Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi>'s Opinions relating there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. By <hi>James Lowde,</hi> Rector of <hi>Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trington</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43329:113"/> in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> ſometime Fellow of <hi>Clare-Hall</hi> in <hi>Cambridge. 8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Apparatus ad Theologiam in uſum Academiarum. 1. Generaiis. 2. Specialis. Auctore</hi> Stephano Penton, <hi>Rectore de</hi> Glympton, Oxon. <hi>8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. Guardians Inſtruction: Or, the Gentleman's Romance. Written for the Diverſion and Service of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. <hi>12o.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. New Inſtructions to the Guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: Shewing that the laſt Remedy to prevent the Ruine, advance the Intereſt, and recover the Honour of this Nation, is, 1. A more ſerious and ſtrict Education of the Nobility and Gentry. 2. To breed up all their younger Sons to ſome Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Employment. 3. More of them to Holy Orders: With a Method of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, from three Years of Age to twenty one. <hi>12o.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. The Doctrine of the Glorious Trinity, not explained, but aſſerted by ſeveral Texts, as they are expounded by the ancient Fathers and later Divines. For the Satisfaction of ſuch as doubt, the Conviction of ſuch as deny, and the Confirmation of ſuch as believe this Myſterious Article of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith.</hi> By <hi>Francis Gregory,</hi> D. D. and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>Hambleden</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks. 8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. A Sermon preached at the Funeral of the Reverend Dr. <hi>John Scot.</hi> By <hi>Z. Iſham,</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Botolph</hi>'s <hi>Biſhop's-gate. 4to.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:43329:113"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
